<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Review, or, A representation of the late sufferings &amp; condition of the dissenters written some years since, but not then suffer'd to come abroad : now publish'd as well to encrease their gratitude to the King for delivering them from all those calamities, as to excite them to joyn vigorously in all lawful means that many conduce to the prevention of their falling under the like, or worse severeties hereafter.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 192KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57105</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">8758701</idno>
  <idno type="VID">41744</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248498166</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25099</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">08758701</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57105)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41744)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1268:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Review, or, A representation of the late sufferings &amp; condition of the dissenters written some years since, but not then suffer'd to come abroad : now publish'd as well to encrease their gratitude to the King for delivering them from all those calamities, as to excite them to joyn vigorously in all lawful means that many conduce to the prevention of their falling under the like, or worse severeties hereafter.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 84 [i.e. 56] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by R. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. 84 [i.e. 56]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41744:1"/>
            <p>THE REVIEW: OR, A Representation of the Late <hi>Sufferings &amp; Condition</hi> OF THE DISSENTERS.</p>
            <p>Written some Years since, but not then Suffer'd to come Abroad.</p>
            <p>Now PUBLISH'D, As well to Encrease their <hi>Gratitude</hi> to the KING, for delivering them from all those <hi>Calamities,</hi> as to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite them to Joyn vigorously in all <hi>Lawful</hi> Means that may conduce to the <hi>prevention</hi> of their falling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>like,</hi> or worse Severities hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Piscator ictus Sapit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:41744:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:41744:2"/>
            <head>An Advertisement to the READERS.</head>
            <p>IT is absolutely necessary you should take notice, That the following Papers were more than prepared for the <hi>Press</hi> several Years ago; But the <hi>high Church-men</hi> to their other rigorous Ʋsages, had added that of <hi>Stopping our Mouths;</hi> and nothing was reckon'd a greater <hi>Crime</hi> in a <hi>Dissenter,</hi> than his Endeavours (how mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destly soever) to Remonstrate that he was <hi>Innocent,</hi> and their Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions against him no less <hi>unreasonable</hi> than <hi>violent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this Mr. <hi>De Laun</hi>'s Case was a terrifying Instance; who, only for writing a Sober and very respective Answer, unto a Doctor of the Church of <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>importunate Challenge</hi> to all <hi>Dissenters,</hi> to come forth and shew <hi>why</hi> they did not Conform, was clapt up in <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, Fined</hi> far beyond, his Ability, and could obtain no Discharge from his tedious Imprisonment, untill the Soveraign Lord Chief Justice of Heaven and Earth was pleased to <hi>remove</hi> him into a better World.</p>
            <p>Thus they first <hi>Gagg'd</hi> us, and then Triumpht and Reproach'd us, That we were <hi>Sullen,</hi> and <hi>would not speak,</hi> or had <hi>nothing to say</hi> for our selves; Whereas indeed it was matter enough for a <hi>Second se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer Lash,</hi> if we did but humbly whisper, That we knew not wherein we had offended, so as justly to deserve the <hi>first.</hi> Nay, sometimes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we spoke not a word, we were cruelly Scourged, (as the <hi>fierce Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sieur</hi> did his Boy) meerly <hi>for Tinking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis no wonder, if such a <hi>dismal Scene</hi> of Affairs, scar'd these <hi>modest Papers</hi> from appearing abroad, during its Continuance; and oblig'd them to take Shelter in a private Recess, where they had lain bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by Oblivion, if an <hi>Auspicious Ray,</hi> had not lately invited them into the publique Light.</p>
            <p>For as Marriners that have happily escaped Shipwrack, take some pleasure when arriv'd on the safe Shore, to look on the <hi>still-threatning</hi> Ocean; and recount both the Dangers they were in, and what means they made use of to avoid the fury of the Storm: So, since it has plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God in his wonderful Providence to Inspire our present <hi>Soveraign</hi> with milder thoughts, and that <hi>He</hi> has graciously vouchsaf'd to knock
<pb facs="tcp:41744:3"/> off all <hi>Conscience-shackles,</hi> by asserting that Generous Christian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, <hi>That none ought to be forced in matters of meer Religion;</hi> I thought the publishing of this well penn'd Discourse might not yet be altogether unuseful; since it both gives an Account of some of those <hi>Reasons</hi> why many sober Persons would not Conform to the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Establishment; And of the <hi>heavy Pressures</hi> they then suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd on that score. As also of the fair <hi>Overtures</hi> and peaceable <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions</hi> they faithfully made in that day of their Distress. And how little all this was regarded by those, who in spite of Christianity, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, and the most submissive Applications, would still proceed in a rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Course of <hi>Destroying</hi> (as far as in them lay) all, whose Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences could not comply with what they thought fit to <hi>Impose.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who the <hi>Author</hi> was or is, I have not been able to Discover, but <hi>the Work</hi> it self speaks him to be both a Master of <hi>Style,</hi> and of a <hi>Judicious Piety;</hi> On whose behalf I thought it necessary to premise thus much; That, understanding for what Season the Book was Calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, you may tde better Excuse diverse <hi>Expressions</hi> relating to those Times, which may not seem so proper for this Juncture, wherein 'tis made publique: And withal, to intreat your Pardon for the nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous (and sometimes gross) <hi>Errata's</hi> of the Press, which the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of an unknow Hand, and other Accidents, rendred almost un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable.</p>
            <p>That there may never be any more Ground for such <hi>Complaints</hi> and <hi>Expostulations;</hi> That those who <hi>occasion'd them,</hi> may repent of their Ʋnchristian Practises therein; And that those that <hi>made them,</hi> may by their holy peaceable <hi>Conversations,</hi> Improve and perpetuate the <hi>unexpected Blessings,</hi> they at present Enjoy; is a Prayer, <hi>wherein</hi> no Serious <hi>well-disposed Christian,</hi> can refuse to joyn, with</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Friend</hi> The Publisher.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:41744:3"/>
            <head>PRECES &amp; LACHRYMAE. <hi>The Introduction.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. WHEN the <hi>Servants</hi> and <hi>Disciples</hi> of the Son of God, were Slandered, Reproached and Persecuted by the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> in the first Age of <hi>Christianity,</hi> they thought it a Duty owing to <hi>Themselves,</hi> their <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>Holy God</hi> that was the <hi>Author</hi> of it, to wipe off those <hi>Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and <hi>Imputations,</hi> and to maintain and defend their <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> against the Injustice and Cruelty of their <hi>Persecutors.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> vindicates himself, sundry times from the Calumnies and Slanders of the <hi>Jews,</hi> as is evident in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Apostles,</hi> and several <hi>Apologetical</hi> Discourses, may be read in his <hi>Epistles,</hi> as also in those of St. <hi>Peter.</hi> The <hi>Apologies</hi> that were written by <hi>Justin Martyr, Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Athenagoras</hi> on the behalf of <hi>Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> are still Extant, known and read by learned Men: Of the same Nature are <hi>Cyprian</hi> to <hi>Demetrianus, Augustin de Civitate dei. Arnobius contra Gentes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. We do not remember that we have either <hi>heard</hi> or <hi>read</hi> that they were denied the <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Complaining,</hi> or asserting their <hi>Innocency,</hi> and the <hi>barbarous Injustice,</hi> of their <hi>Persecutors.</hi> Those that Prosecuted them were Persons sufficiently <hi>Inhumane,</hi> yet they never forbad, or punished them, for avowing their own <hi>Integ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> or groaning under the Rods, wherewith they made them bleed. 'Twas never Penal to be <hi>Sensible</hi> of their infelicities, nor to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm themselves <hi>Upright,</hi> when they were Treated as <hi>Transgres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. 'Tis not our purpose to affirm our Sufferings, equal with those of the <hi>Primitive Christians,</hi> or that we have the same <hi>Reasons</hi> of
<pb facs="tcp:41744:4"/> Complaint. We do readily acknowledg, that our Calamities are as much <hi>Inferiour</hi> to theirs, as are our <hi>Piety</hi> and our <hi>Virtues;</hi> and the comparison as <hi>Unequal</hi> on the one part as the other. But though these be not <hi>Equally</hi> great, with these of those <hi>Eminent</hi> and very <hi>Holy Persons:</hi> we think them severe enough to justifie a <hi>Complaint</hi> and unreasonable enough to allow an <hi>Accusation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That our State and Condition is <hi>Calamitous</hi> can't be denied. Almost all the <hi>Cities, Towns</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> in <hi>England</hi> with wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness can affiirm it; All the <hi>Prisons, Courts</hi> and <hi>Tribunals</hi> in the <hi>Land</hi> will give their <hi>Suffrage</hi> to it; and they must live in great <hi>Privacy</hi> and <hi>Retirement,</hi> that do not <hi>sufficiently</hi> understand it, from their own <hi>knowledg</hi> and <hi>observation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. All manner of <hi>evil Things,</hi> are reported concerning us, and there is almost nothing <hi>Impious</hi> and <hi>Infamous,</hi> which is not laid to our Charge. The many <hi>Books</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets</hi> that are written; the many <hi>Sermons</hi> that are preached, before <hi>Judges, Magistrates,</hi> and Persons in Authority and Office; the daily <hi>Libels</hi> that the Press doth <hi>Spawn,</hi> on purpose to defame, and make us an abhorrence, are such <hi>evidence</hi> of it, as cannot be gainesaid.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Our Case being such, we will take the <hi>liberty</hi> that was permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the <hi>Christians</hi> of Old; and hope we may do it with <hi>Impunity,</hi> we will presume that we may have <hi>Licence,</hi> to groan under our bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and express the sense we have, of the <hi>weight</hi> and <hi>uneasie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness</hi> of them; we can't but feell the <hi>Severities</hi> that are excercised towards us, nor can we be without some Resentments of those <hi>hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid</hi> and <hi>mischievious Imputations,</hi> that with impudence, and face of <hi>Brass,</hi> are said to our Prejudice, and disadvantage. We will therefore, complaine of the <hi>Impositions</hi> and <hi>Burdens,</hi> that lye up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us; we will <hi>Expostulate</hi> with our <hi>Persecutors;</hi> we will in most <hi>Humble</hi> and <hi>Prostrate</hi> manner make our <hi>Supplications</hi> before them; and lastly avow our <hi>Innocency,</hi> and purposes of <hi>Perseverance</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and this we intend to do, very briefly, and with a becoming Modesty, Freedom and Candour.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41744:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. I</hi> The DISSENTERS Complaints. (To speak at first once for all, Take notice that I charge not every Church of <hi>England</hi> man with Malignancy, or such a Spirit of Persecution, nor that I go about to vindicate every single Dissenter.)</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE Terms of <hi>Communion</hi> imposed upon our Ministers and required of us, are of <hi>unnecessary nature, uncertain truth,</hi> and though true, yet <hi>impossible</hi> to be submitted to, by many, with <hi>understanding</hi> and <hi>judgment.</hi> Those among us that are <hi>Clergy-Men,</hi> are obliged in all publick <hi>holy Offices</hi> and <hi>Administrations,</hi> to wear the <hi>Surplice,</hi> Baptize with <hi>Godfathers,</hi> and the <hi>Sign of the Cross,</hi> give the Sacrament <hi>kneeling,</hi> and deny it to all such as refuse to receive it in that Gesture. But what necessity is there of these things? Were they imposed by <hi>Jesus Christ</hi> or his <hi>Apostles?</hi> Did St. <hi>Paul</hi> wear a Surplice, or St. <hi>Peter</hi> Baptise with the <hi>Sign</hi> of the Cross. Are these things <hi>Essential</hi> to Christian Religion? Cannot the Churches of God in this Nation, yea, cannot the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> subsist without the use and practice of them? If any man think so, let him enjoy his <hi>Opinion,</hi> we are not like to be his Converts. There were <hi>Churches</hi> in being before these things were known or observed, and we are of the mind there may be again when the use and memory of them may fail upon Earth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Minister that Conforms, is bound to affirm it <hi>certain</hi> by <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Word,</hi> That Children dying after <hi>Baptism,</hi> before the Commission of <hi>Actual Sin,</hi> are certainly <hi>saved.</hi> Now that <hi>some Children</hi> so dying are certainly <hi>saved,</hi> we do heartily believe. We think, that the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise</hi> is made to <hi>Believers and their Seed;</hi> and that the Children of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents</hi> that dye before actual sin are saved. But whether the Children of <hi>Atheists, Papists, Infidels</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> that are Baptised, and expire before <hi>actual Transgressions,</hi> are immediately advanced in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Presence</hi> of God, and Conversation of the <hi>Blessed,</hi> is a thing of which we are not certain, nor can we find any Proof of it in the Gospel. In the mean time we do not pretend to condemn, or judg concerning them. We leave them to God who is their <hi>Judg,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ill deal <hi>righteously</hi> by them, and all the World besides.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41744:5"/>3. That all the <hi>Heathens</hi> are damned, is <hi>Virtually</hi> asserted in the <hi>Thirty Nine Articles,</hi> (which all that are admitted to minister in holy things must subscribe) but of this we are not very sure, and we think that we have read that <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> and some others of the Fathers, were of other apprehensions in that Case: And there are some in this Age, as well as in those which have preceded, that have entertained <hi>some hopes of the Salvation</hi> of some of them. Mr. <hi>Humsrey</hi> hath said many things with great consideration and judgment in favour of that Opinion, in his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaceable Disquisitions.</hi> And we do avow to all the World, that we do believe, that no man can be sure of their universal D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnation; and that to our appehension 'tis more likely, that <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus, Epicutetus, Plato, Plotinus,</hi> and many others are in Heaven, than many of those that have been reputed Saints, and placed among the Blessed there. Not that any are saved without a <hi>Saviour,</hi> or sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied without the Influences of the <hi>Holy Ghost.</hi> We do firmly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that there is <hi>no Name under Heaven given unto Men whereby they may be saved, but the Name of Jesus of Nazareth;</hi> but as there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny persons that do receive gifts of mercy, kindness and benevolence from unknown hands, so we humbly conceive the <hi>Heathens</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive pardon of sin from an <hi>unknown Saviour,</hi> and a holy and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Nature from an unknown <hi>holy</hi> Spirit.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That the <hi>Church</hi> hath power to appoint <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> is also affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Articles thereof, but we see nothing that proves the <hi>indefinite</hi> truth of that Proposition. If by <hi>Ceremonies</hi> are meant the necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry circumstances of action, and as are by consequence, and involution commanded in, and with those actions and duties wherewithal they are involved we do easily grant it. But if thereby you mean Rite that are exhibitive of <hi>Grace,</hi> yea, or significations of <hi>Duty,</hi> we mus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> demur a little, for we think Christ Jesus the Law-giver of his Church and that he hath given Laws enough for its <hi>Constitution</hi> and <hi>Admini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stration.</hi> Besides we desire to know of what Extent this Power of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Church is, and what are the Limits of it: If it hath no Limits, thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> it may introduce a Yoke upon Christians, much more insupportabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> than what was laid upon the Jews; and yet that was such, (the Apostl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> affirms) <hi>as neither they nor their Fathers were able to bear, Acts</hi> 15. If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath any bounds, we would fain understand who hath fixed, or wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> must determine them. If it be said that God hath set, and establis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed them in his Word we do willingly assent unto it, and add farthe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that by the <hi>perfection</hi> and <hi>sufficiency</hi> of his <hi>Laws,</hi> we think he hath d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>termined it to a <hi>Point,</hi> for to what purpose a <hi>needless and useless Pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> (and such it must be if Christ's Law be perfect) should be granted to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41744:5"/>
                  <hi>Church,</hi> we can not understand. If it be said that the <hi>Church</hi> it self must fix the <hi>bounds</hi> of its <hi>Power,</hi> 'tis much the same as if it were utterly without any. For 'tis to be supposed that they will affirm, that how nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous soever their <hi>Ceremonious</hi> Impositions be they go not beyond their power, and so farewel all Christian Liberty. Christ Jesus hath only purchased an Exchange, but no Freedom from a <hi>Yoke of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</hi> And truly we think the Exchange is to our prejudice, for 'tis more eligible to bear the burthen and impositions that a <hi>wise</hi> and <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God</hi> doth lay upon us, than those that are laid upon us by <hi>foolish</hi> and sometimes <hi>imperious</hi> and <hi>wicked</hi> men.</p>
               <p n="5">5. 'Tis said in the beginning of the <hi>Athanasian Creed,</hi> that <hi>whosoever will be saved</hi> must believe the <hi>Catholick Faith,</hi> and that whosoever doth not keep it <hi>whole and undefiled,</hi> without <hi>doubt</hi> shall perish <hi>everlastingly:</hi> and in the conclusion 'tis determined, that if a man doth not faithfully believe the Doctrine thereof he cannot be saved. Which Doctrine, as also the damnatory Sentences affixed unto it must be subscribed by all that will serve <hi>God</hi> in the Work of Preaching the Gospel with the licence and favour of Authority. We do very vehemently assert the Deity of our <hi>Saviour;</hi> and that he is both God and Man in one Person; and that one in three, and and three in one is of the Essence of Christianity. But whether all that do not believe it in the sense and explication of <hi>Athanasius</hi> are certainly damned, seems to us very uncertain, and we are unwilling to avow the truth of it, lest we should condemn the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration os the Just. We do believe that many thousands of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians were saved before that <hi>Creed</hi> was known in the World; and we do not doubt but many might and would be saved though it should pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish from among Men. We think it sufficient that the Doctrine of the Trinity, and Union of the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Humane</hi> Natures in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of our Lord Jesus, be believed in those general and indefinite Terms under which 'tis expressed in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and that whosoever believes it so (supposing him otherwise qualified for it) will certainly be saved; though he should not understand (as few plain Christians do) nor believe the Explanations of <hi>Athanasius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether the <hi>Explanatory</hi> Doctrine of the Creed called by his Name (though written some Ages since his Death, as is thought by some learned Men) be <hi>punctually true</hi> we will not affirm, but this we will say, that if it be true, 'tis impossible that many, if not most, that do subscribe and avow the truth of it, should do it with understanding and conviction of judgment, and conscience. The Doctrine of the <hi>Trinity</hi> and Personal <hi>Ʋnion,</hi> according as 'tis there delivered, is Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of such abstruse speculations, and Ministers matter for so many <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:41744:6"/> not easily to be answered, that we think it a mighty difficulty, for any man with Judgment and Satisfaction of mind, to subscribe to it, and impossible for those many unstudied Novices that take Holy Orders, and enter into the Church. They have neither <hi>Parts</hi> nor <hi>Patience,</hi> nor <hi>prepatory Learning</hi> and <hi>Knowledge,</hi> for the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of so <hi>sublime</hi> a <hi>Theory;</hi> and there is no man that hath, with any seriousness, applied himself to such <hi>Meditations</hi> (we think) that will not easily conceive it.</p>
               <p n="7">7. 'Tis said in the Book of <hi>Ordination,</hi> that by <hi>reading old Authors</hi> and <hi>Writers of the Church, 'tis evident that there have been, even from the daies of the Apostles, three Orders in the Church,</hi> viz. <hi>Bishops, Priests</hi> and <hi>Deacons.</hi> Whether this Doctrine be <hi>true</hi> is not the business of these <hi>Papers</hi> to determine; but we will be so bold as to <hi>affirm</hi> that we think it scarcely <hi>possible,</hi> that <hi>most</hi> of those that do acknowledg the <hi>truth</hi> of it, should do it with <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>steddy</hi> assurance of mind. There are men of good <hi>Learning, Reading, Age,</hi> and <hi>Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>deration,</hi> that have professed great <hi>uncertainty</hi> and <hi>irresolution</hi> in the point. When they read what <hi>Jerome</hi> saies in his Commentaries on <hi>Titus,</hi> and in his <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pistle</hi> to <hi>Evagrius,</hi> and other places of his Writings, they are ready to embrace a <hi>Presbyterian</hi> parity, and acknowledg no <hi>Prelation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Bishops</hi> and <hi>Priests,</hi> but what is either by <hi>consent</hi> or <hi>humane Laws</hi> and <hi>Constitutions.</hi> When they read other <hi>passages</hi> in that same Author, wherein he seems to <hi>contradict</hi> himself, they are inclined to acknowledge a <hi>prelatical Episcopacy.</hi> When they read the <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles</hi> of <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> they cannot deny a <hi>Prelacy:</hi> but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be a <hi>Prelacy</hi> in one and the same <hi>particular Church,</hi> or in and over the <hi>Presbyters</hi> of <hi>many Churches;</hi> and whether it be a <hi>Divine</hi> or <hi>Humane</hi> Appointment, they are not <hi>very much</hi> assured. And if those that have <hi>read</hi> and <hi>considered</hi> the point, cannot satisfie their <hi>minds,</hi> or come to a determination about it, how is it possible that such as <hi>never read,</hi> or <hi>thought</hi> almost any thing on that <hi>Subject</hi> (and such are most that enter the <hi>Sacred Off ce</hi>) can with <hi>Judgment</hi> and <hi>convicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of <hi>Conscience,</hi> subscribe the truth of it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. We have not here set down <hi>all those things</hi> that we think <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>necessary, uncertain,</hi> and <hi>impossible</hi> to be consented to, with a <hi>satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied understanding,</hi> in the terms of <hi>Communion,</hi> required by this <hi>Church,</hi> for then we must have written a <hi>Volume,</hi> whereas we intend only a <hi>few sheets.</hi> We have proposed some <hi>very few Examples,</hi> from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst <hi>the many</hi> that might have been produced, had it consisted with our <hi>designed</hi> brevity. Whoever shall apply himself to the <hi>Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of them, will easily observe <hi>many others</hi> of like kind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:41744:6"/>
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THE Forms of <hi>Subscription</hi> and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enunciation</hi> that are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of us, are <hi>expressed</hi> in words <hi>too bold, indefinite, peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory,</hi> and <hi>dogmatical.</hi> By the <hi>Six and Thirtieth Canon,</hi> all that are admitted to the Sacred Office are obliged <hi>willingly</hi> and <hi>ex animo</hi> to subscribe, That <hi>the Book of Common Prayer,</hi> and <hi>of ordering Bishops, Priests</hi> and <hi>Deacons, contain nothing contrary to the word of God;</hi> and <hi>that they allow and acknowledg the Book of Articles, being in number</hi> 39, <hi>to be agreeable to the Word of God.</hi> Betwixt Truth and Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shood there is no <hi>medium,</hi> that we know or understand. What is not contrary to the Word of God is of equal truth with it. What is agreeable thereunto, is as indisputable as the inspired Volumes. And <hi>what</hi> is this we pray, but to advance the Opinions and Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, the Books and Writings of solid men, to an equality of truth, with those that were written by the Inspiration and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Holy Ghost.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We do profess, that we do not see, how <hi>Subscription</hi> can be made to any Translation of the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> in that Form of Words; for that there is <hi>nothing</hi> in <hi>any,</hi> even in the <hi>best</hi> Translati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, contrary to the <hi>Original</hi> Text, or that all things in any one of them are <hi>agreeable</hi> thereunto, is we think a very bold and daring Assertion: Yea, we will add thus much farther, that we know not how any man can affirm concerning the <hi>Original it self,</hi> that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains nothing contrary to what was written by the <hi>inspired</hi> Authors. That the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew</hi> Copies have received no <hi>change</hi> or <hi>varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> is we think <hi>impossible</hi> to be proved; and those that shall <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare</hi> the most <hi>Ancient</hi> Translations with the present Original Copies, will find, that if they had not read <hi>otherwise</hi> than <hi>now</hi> we do, it were <hi>impossible</hi> they should have <hi>Translated</hi> as they did. For proof of this, we must refer the Reader to <hi>Ludovicus Cappelegus</hi> his <hi>Critica,</hi> and Father <hi>Simon</hi> on that Subject, whose Book is lately Translated into the <hi>English</hi> Tongue. In the mean while, we intend not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sparage or invalidate the Authority of the <hi>Original</hi> Text. We do with very great assurance affirm, that the variations that may have happened therein, are not <hi>material,</hi> and that the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>manners,</hi> the <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>salvation</hi> of men, can suffer <hi>no prejudice,</hi> nor run no <hi>hazzards</hi> thereby.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:41744:7"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE are not permitted to make <hi>explications,</hi> nor to declare our <hi>sense</hi> of the Subscriptions, Declarations, and Oaths that are imposed upon us. They are formed in <hi>Ambiguous</hi> Words, and such as are capable of <hi>sundry acceptations,</hi> but in which of them we <hi>understand,</hi> and could <hi>take,</hi> and <hi>submit</hi> unto them, we are not <hi>allowed to say.</hi> They must be <hi>swallowed</hi> in the lump, without any chewing. No sense of <hi>savour</hi> may be put upon them, though sense be sufficient to search the <hi>Government,</hi> and agreeable to the Laws of the Land</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the Conformable <hi>Gentry</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> (we mean such as are men of <hi>conscience</hi> and <hi>consideration</hi>) do put a <hi>favourable sense</hi> and <hi>interpretation</hi> upon them, we are sufficiently assured by their <hi>Books,</hi> and the <hi>Conversation</hi> we have with some of them. And so <hi>favourable, candid</hi> and <hi>engenuous,</hi> is the sense they give of them, that might we be permitted to <hi>declare</hi> it, we our <hi>selves,</hi> at least very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of us, could submit unto them; but this is a <hi>fovour</hi> that is not allowed us, 'tis an <hi>indulgence</hi> that hath not been granted us, nor for ought that we can <hi>perceive,</hi> is like to be.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Were we satisfied that we might take the required <hi>Subscriptions, Declarations</hi> and <hi>Oaths</hi> in our own sense, without declaring our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication; we might long since many of us have been <hi>Conformists,</hi> or might be suddenly so, but that is a thing in which we cannot be as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sured. If such a <hi>Liberty</hi> be taken we think the <hi>Impossition,</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring</hi> of them will be of little <hi>use,</hi> or <hi>signification,</hi> because it is no great difficulty by <hi>Interpretations,</hi> and mollisying <hi>expositions</hi> in our minds, to enervate the <hi>force,</hi> and void the <hi>obligation of all</hi> the <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Subscriptions</hi> in the World.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We know, that there is a <hi>mean</hi> betwixt a <hi>rigorous, strictt, severe,</hi> and a <hi>loose, vagous</hi> and <hi>licentious Intrepretation;</hi> but we do also know that 'tis no easie manner to find it; and that all men that may be concerned in such things, are not skilled in <hi>splitting hairs,</hi> or <hi>divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Attoms,</hi> that persons of <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>scrupulous Consciences,</hi> will be everlastingly zealous lest they should <hi>poise</hi> the <hi>Golden Mean,</hi> and embrace the <hi>loose</hi> and <hi>vagous</hi> sense and exposition.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41744:7"/>5. If this <hi>scrupulosity</hi> of Conscience be a Fault, 'tis such as very good men are liable unto, and know not how to remedy it. To be afraid of sin, is (we are sure) a very <hi>commendable quality,</hi> and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of <hi>encouragement</hi> and <hi>praise.</hi> If any be <hi>superstitiously</hi> timorous, and fear where no fear is, we think them worthy of <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>indulgence,</hi> and that in <hi>Impositions, Oaths</hi> and <hi>Subscriptions,</hi> it ought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, that there are, and ever will be such men in the World; and therefore that such things be never required, but in cases of <hi>great</hi> and <hi>absolute</hi> necessity, in <hi>plain, obvious,</hi> and necessary things; and that the forms in which they are proposed, be drawn with great <hi>wariness</hi> and <hi>caution,</hi> and expressed in words of <hi>Common use,</hi> and as free as possible from all <hi>ambiguity</hi> of signification.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHEN the Doors of the Church are to us made impassa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by the <hi>Turn-Pikes</hi> and <hi>Port-Cullis</hi> that are set before it, we are Excommunicated and delivered over to <hi>Satan</hi> because we do not come into it. This we must confess is an extraordinary method of proceeding. We find nothing of this nature in the Scripture, or in the practice of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church. Nothing was required as antecedently necessary to <hi>Church-Communion,</hi> but <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>simple Christianity.</hi> There were no <hi>Articles, Liturgy,</hi> or Book of <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to be subscribed; There were no <hi>Declarations, Oaths, Abjurations</hi> to be made to qualifie persons for admission thereunto. Assent and Consent to the <hi>Baptismal Covenant,</hi> was then thought sufficient, and would be so still, if we that have less wisdom and understanding, did not presume we have more, than the <hi>Apostl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> and <hi>Primitive Christians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We do very easily acknowledge <hi>Excomunication</hi> a sacred and tremendous Ordinance, <hi>summum futuri judicis prejudicium, Tertul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> calls it; and 'tis our Opinion, that when 'tis exercised, it ought to be done with <hi>great</hi> gravity and seriousness, <hi>magno cum pondere, ut apud certos de Dei conspectu;</hi> and upon very <hi>weighty</hi> and <hi>important</hi> reasons. To do it with an inserious trifling spirit, and for <hi>impertinene</hi> and <hi>invaluable</hi> causes and pretences (as is the custom of these days) is to <hi>prophane</hi> it, and make it <hi>cheap</hi> and <hi>contemptible;</hi> and peradventure it may be a greater <hi>Blasphemy</hi> than some men are well aware of or <hi>duely</hi> consider.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41744:8"/>3. In the <hi>Scripture</hi> we find some persons put under this <hi>divine Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure,</hi> but it was for <hi>great</hi> and <hi>obvious</hi> transgressions of the <hi>divine</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; St. <hi>Paul</hi> judged the <hi>incestuous Corinthian</hi> to be delivered unto <hi>Satan;</hi> and he himself did so by <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Philetus:</hi> But the one had married his <hi>Fathers</hi> Wife, and the other had made <hi>Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack</hi> of the <hi>Christian Faith.</hi> These men were a reproach to the Christian Name; and therefore it was their duty to disown and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject them from their <hi>Communion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> we do also find men put under the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Excommunication;</hi> but it was usually for denying the Faith, and sacrificing to Idols in Times of Persecution, or for delivering up the <hi>Books</hi> of the holy <hi>Scriptures</hi> into the <hi>hands</hi> of their Enemies, or for some other gross and scandalous Crimes. We do not find that they imposed <hi>useless, unnecessary, uncertain,</hi> and <hi>controverted</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines as <hi>terms</hi> and <hi>conditions</hi> of <hi>Church-Communion,</hi> and then Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated such as could not <hi>consent</hi> unto them. This was a Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice unknown in the <hi>purest Ages</hi> of the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Victor</hi> Bishop of <hi>Rome</hi> was the first <hi>Ʋndertaker</hi> in this kind: (besides those that we read of; <hi>Act.</hi> 15.) he would have imposed the <hi>Roman</hi> Custom of observing <hi>Easter</hi> upon the <hi>Asiatick</hi> Churches; and because they refused it, he at least threatned them with Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication; for <hi>Valesius</hi> thinks he did not actually do it; and 'tis possible that the Letters of <hi>Ireneus</hi> and others, might prevent the <hi>execution</hi> of his angry purposes and determinations.</p>
               <p n="6">6. We are sorry to see the present <hi>Modes</hi> and <hi>ways</hi> of proceeding in use among us. Humane <hi>Appointments</hi> and <hi>Constitutions</hi> are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon us; things unnecessary and doubtful are required of us, and because we <hi>refuse</hi> them, we are given up to the <hi>Devil;</hi> and truly our <hi>Case</hi> were sad, did we not <hi>hope</hi> for more <hi>favour</hi> from God, than we do <hi>receive</hi> or <hi>expect</hi> from men. For we must stand before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Tribunal,</hi> and have some hope to be acquitted there, though we be <hi>condemned</hi> here. <hi>Multa etenim facta quae hominibus improbanda viderentur, testimonio tuo domino approbata sunt. Aug. in confessioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:41744:8"/>
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p>THE Penal <hi>Laws</hi> are executed upon us with great <hi>rage</hi> and <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> and there are scarcely any <hi>executions</hi> that are thought <hi>sufficiently</hi> severe. Should we enumerate our <hi>sufferings,</hi> the History of them would <hi>swell</hi> into sundry <hi>Volumes,</hi> which is not the <hi>design</hi> of this Discourse. We intend no full <hi>accurate</hi> description of our <hi>calamities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We are not ignorant, that those that <hi>prosecute</hi> us, think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves sufficienty <hi>justified</hi> in all that they do against us by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the <hi>Laws;</hi> we are of another opinion, and so (we make no doubt) will they be <hi>another day.</hi> Those that persecuted the <hi>Christians</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Times,</hi> did it by the authority of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and so did they in <hi>Germany</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth; in the Low Countries in the time of Duke <hi>Alva</hi>'s Government; and in <hi>England</hi> in the Reign of Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> and so they do now in <hi>France</hi> under the Rule of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 14th.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are few <hi>Protestants</hi> but will condemn those <hi>persecutions,</hi> though they were directed by the <hi>Laws;</hi> and we think it no easie matter to justifie the <hi>prosecutions</hi> that are made against us, although those that afflict us, have the Laws to plead on their behalf. We think the <hi>Laws</hi> are no better than their <hi>Authors;</hi> and we are sure they were <hi>men</hi> subject to like <hi>passions</hi> with other <hi>Mortals,</hi> and never gave any evidence of <hi>infallible</hi> direction, or <hi>inspiration</hi> in the <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance</hi> or making of them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. No <hi>Laws</hi> can justifie <hi>prosecutions</hi> or <hi>Prosecutors,</hi> but such as are just. Where they are unjust, those that suffer by them are the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> persons, and those that prosecute them are the <hi>Offenders.</hi> 'Tis against the <hi>Law</hi> in <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> to read the <hi>Bible</hi> in the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of those <hi>Countries;</hi> but those that persecute such as trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gress that <hi>Law,</hi> are <hi>transgr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ssors;</hi> and those that are outraged and tormented by them, are therein <hi>innocent,</hi> and probably very good <hi>Christians.</hi> 'Twas against the <hi>Law</hi> to make <hi>any Petition</hi> to <hi>God</hi> or <hi>man for the space of thirty days,</hi> unless to <hi>Darius</hi> the King. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, we esteem <hi>Daniel</hi> that transgressed the <hi>Law,</hi> as a much better man than any of them that prosecuted him for the breach of it.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41744:9"/>5. The <hi>Laws</hi> require of us the practice of things <hi>unnecessary</hi> to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribe to things <hi>doubtful,</hi> and not at all <hi>essential</hi> to the <hi>Christian</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, to swear to <hi>Propositions doubtful,</hi> if not denied by men of <hi>great</hi> learning and sobriety. The refusal of these things is <hi>penal,</hi> some of us are thereby disabled publickly to <hi>preach</hi> the <hi>Gospel,</hi> and others to <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend</hi> it: and if we preach or hear, or worship God in <hi>private</hi> in the Communion of more than <hi>five,</hi> besides the Family in which such <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> is performed, we are exposed to punishments more than <hi>many,</hi> and those none of the <hi>smallest</hi> or <hi>gentlest</hi> kinds.</p>
               <p n="6">6. If the imposing things of <hi>this nature,</hi> to be <hi>sworn, subscribed</hi> and <hi>declared,</hi> and the punishing men for the <hi>refusal</hi> of them, and worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God by other <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> than those prescribed by the <hi>English Liturgy,</hi> be just in themselves, or will justifie our <hi>Persecutors,</hi> we despair of understanding any thing of the natures of <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil.</hi> But of the unreasonableness, and <hi>injustice</hi> of impositions (and the <hi>impossibility</hi> of uniting the Church by them, See a little Book called the <hi>Samaritane.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p n="1">1 THough the <hi>Penalties</hi> imposed on us by the <hi>Laws,</hi> be severe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, yet did we suffer no more than the <hi>Law</hi> directs, we should not have <hi>so much,</hi> nor so <hi>many reasons</hi> to <hi>complain,</hi> but alas, the <hi>Laws</hi> are not <hi>keen</hi> enough to wound us, nor <hi>sharp</hi> enough to draw <hi>blood</hi> to the satisfaction of our <hi>enemies,</hi> the Informers, who are <hi>insati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able</hi> in their <hi>malice,</hi> their <hi>hatred</hi> and their <hi>rage.</hi> The little <hi>fingers</hi> of our Prosecutors are <hi>heavier</hi> than the <hi>Loins of the Law;</hi> if the one <hi>chastife</hi> us with <hi>Rods,</hi> the other does <hi>correct</hi> us with <hi>Scorpions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The old <hi>musty Statutes,</hi> that were made and intended to the prejudice of the Papists, tho seldom or never <hi>executed</hi> upon them, are <hi>turned</hi> by these Informers against us <hi>with severity and height of Indignation,</hi> and we think we may safely say, that more <hi>true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> have been <hi>worried, ruined and undone</hi> by them in the space of half <hi>one year,</hi> than <hi>Papists</hi> in neer an <hi>hundred.</hi> Those <hi>Rods</hi> that were made to <hi>scourge</hi> them are dipped in <hi>Brine,</hi> and laid on our backs with <hi>strokes,</hi> till the <hi>flesh, blood</hi> and <hi>bones</hi> appear. They escape the <hi>Curse</hi> of the <hi>Statutes,</hi> but we die <hi>without mercy,</hi> and can find no <hi>remedy</hi> from their <hi>vengeance. Dat veniam Corvis, vexat censura columbas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:41744:9"/>3. To which we will add, The <hi>Laws</hi> sometimes seen to be put upon Tenters, and extended to such <hi>uses</hi> and <hi>significations,</hi> as is likely never entred into the <hi>minds</hi> of those that made them. Any <hi>Comentary</hi> is sound and good, though it perverts the <hi>Text,</hi> provided it may serve the turn of our Enemies the <hi>Informers.</hi> And there is, almost, no <hi>Statute,</hi> that may not by a dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous <hi>ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>osition,</hi> become an <hi>instrument</hi> of our ruine, as we find by very <hi>dismal</hi> experience, almost every day. These Men are marvelously <hi>ingenious</hi> to destroy us; and 'tis a strange <hi>Law</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed in which they can find nothing to <hi>promote</hi> it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We have heard, or read, that in the dayes of our <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> it was thought a good <hi>wholesom</hi> rule, that <hi>penal Laws</hi> were to be construed in the most <hi>favourable</hi> sense, that the words were capable of bearing; but the men of <hi>this age,</hi> our <hi>Prosecutors,</hi> are of other perswasions, that old worm eaten <hi>maxime</hi> is now of no <hi>value</hi> or <hi>reputation,</hi> at least in such <hi>cases</hi> where <hi>we</hi> are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. The <hi>severest</hi> sense that can be put upon them, is the only <hi>rule</hi> and <hi>measure</hi> of interpretation, yea, senses <hi>more severe</hi> then can with any <hi>reason</hi> be affixed unto them, are esteemed very <hi>lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable</hi> Expositions. All senses are good with them that will do us <hi>hurt,</hi> and all <hi>coments</hi> lawful, that may be serviceable to our <hi>cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> and <hi>affliction.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE have been in some places punished for <hi>faults</hi> that we never <hi>committed,</hi> and prosecuted for our presence at <hi>Conventicles</hi> where we never were. This we think is hard <hi>measure,</hi> but 'tis no other than what we have had <hi>experience</hi> of.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Those men upon whose <hi>Evidence</hi> and <hi>Oaths,</hi> some of us have been convicted, are persons <hi>viler than the Earth,</hi> their <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> we would have scorned to have set among <hi>the Dogs of our Flocks.</hi> They are the <hi>dregs</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>abhorence</hi> of all that know or have any <hi>conversation</hi> with them. Their <hi>Debaucheries</hi> have beggered and <hi>impoverished</hi> them to that degree, that they take up this trade. Their <hi>Words</hi> and their <hi>Oaths</hi> will not be taken, among their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> for a Groat.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:41744:10"/>3. We have heard or read, that according to our <hi>Laws,</hi> those that receive <hi>Evidence</hi> against any <hi>subject</hi> of the Realm, ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider the <hi>quality</hi> and <hi>credibility</hi> of him, or them that give it, and there <hi>seems</hi> to be a great deal of <hi>reason</hi> for it, for otherwise our <hi>Estates,</hi> our <hi>Reputation,</hi> and our <hi>Lives,</hi> are all at the mercy and in the dispo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal of all such <hi>Varlets,</hi> as have so much <hi>need,</hi> and so little <hi>conscience,</hi> as to make merchandize of them. How well this <hi>good</hi> and charitable <hi>rule</hi> hath been observed in those <hi>testimonies</hi> that have been taken against us, we are not willing to say.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It is readily granted that those <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> to whom these <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>screants</hi> offer their <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Depositions,</hi> cannot refuse them, because they <hi>themselves</hi> become <hi>criminal,</hi> and liable to prosecutions at <hi>Law</hi> thereby. But we do humbly conceive, that when we appeal to the <hi>Sessions,</hi> which is a Court of <hi>Judicature,</hi> where they either are our <hi>Judges,</hi> our <hi>Jury,</hi> or both; the quality of the <hi>Witnesses</hi> and <hi>Deponents,</hi> ought to be considered, especially when we bring <hi>evidence sufficient</hi> to disable all their <hi>attestations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE are ruined in our <hi>Estates</hi> and <hi>Fortunes;</hi> our Houses are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up, the <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Furniture</hi> whereof are <hi>violently</hi> taken from us, and whatever we have any <hi>propriety</hi> in, is taken out of our <hi>possessions.</hi> Those that <hi>spoil</hi> us shew us no <hi>mercy,</hi> they are <hi>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>xorable</hi> to all our <hi>Intreaties</hi> and <hi>Complaints.</hi> If we tell them that by the <hi>seizure</hi> and <hi>sale</hi> of our <hi>Goods,</hi> our Persons and Families are beggered, and brought to a <hi>morsel</hi> of Bread, 'tis to as good <hi>purpose,</hi> as if we discoursed to the same sense to the <hi>Wolves</hi> of the Deserts. What evidence they do give to <hi>others</hi> that they are <hi>men,</hi> we do not know, but we are <hi>able to infer it,</hi> from no other <hi>argument</hi> but their shape.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All the <hi>Applications</hi> that we make to them for <hi>mercy</hi> or <hi>favour,</hi> are rejected with insolent <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>scorn;</hi> the most modest and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Petitions</hi> and <hi>Supplications,</hi> are received with <hi>rage</hi> and <hi>indignation.</hi> Tis a crime to beg any <hi>abatement</hi> or <hi>remissions</hi> of the utmost <hi>severities</hi> of the <hi>Laws;</hi> and some that have been <hi>uneasie</hi> and complained of the <hi>burden</hi> of them, we are inclined to think, will complain no more, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no mind to be lashed whilst they are raw.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The usual answer that is made to all the <hi>Addresses,</hi> that we make unto them, is this, <hi>You are a company of factious Fanatiques, and you must bear the penalties of the Statutes;</hi> and we have born them so
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41744:10"/> long, some of us, that we can bear them <hi>no more.</hi> For how they will <hi>destrain</hi> upon those that have no <hi>Goods,</hi> we cannot easily understand, nor how the <hi>mulcts</hi> will be paid by insolent <hi>persons,</hi> we are not able to <hi>divine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. We take no <hi>pleasure</hi> in these <hi>Narrations,</hi> and we hope we may be <hi>believed,</hi> when we say, that we are <hi>sorry</hi> that we have any <hi>occasion</hi> for them; but truth is truth, losers will talk. Those that are pinch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed will go near to complain. We are no <hi>Stoicks,</hi> we have not put off the <hi>Passions</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> of <hi>Humane Nature,</hi> nor are we like to do, tho, perhaps, we may have <hi>reason</hi> to wish it a thing <hi>possible.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IX.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE are imprisoned and laid in <hi>Goals</hi> among Rogues. We are made (at least) <hi>neighbours</hi> to those that are the lees of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Our restraint is a <hi>Calamity,</hi> but the Neighborhood of these <hi>Varlets,</hi> make it much more heavy and <hi>insupportable.</hi> Their <hi>swearing</hi> and <hi>blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy,</hi> their <hi>Midnight Revels</hi> and <hi>Debaucheries</hi> (which we cannot cease to hear) are a perpetual <hi>offence</hi> unto us; and we think it a cruelty much like that of <hi>chaining the Living</hi> to the Dead.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis true sometimes we have <hi>good company</hi> more than we do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire, for we are thrown by <hi>heaps</hi> into Prisons and Places of Restraint. But though the presence of our <hi>Friends</hi> be pleasant, and their <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation</hi> lovely, and we could heartily rejoyce in it elsewhere; 'tis no so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace to us to have them <hi>Companions</hi> in our Griefs, or <hi>Copartners</hi> in our Calamities, and we should <hi>rejoyce</hi> in their <hi>liberty</hi> though we our selves were bound.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If we survive our Imprisonment, (which we do not alwaies do) and return again to our <hi>own houses,</hi> we bring along with us the <hi>founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of those Diseases, that in some space and tract of time do bring us to <hi>our Graves.</hi> The closeness of our <hi>Lodgings,</hi> the thickness, impurity, and corruption of the Air, the want of due <hi>exercise</hi> to move and agitate the <hi>humors</hi> of our Bodies, and preserve them from <hi>stagnation,</hi> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws our very <hi>Crasis</hi> and Constitution, and thence proceeds those <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seases,</hi> that no art can cure or remove.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Suppose that by <hi>care</hi> and <hi>art</hi> our Lives be a little prolonged, we are a burthen to our <hi>selves,</hi> and all that are about us. And whereas other men die but <hi>once,</hi> we die a <hi>thousand times,</hi> and as often stab to the <hi>heart</hi> all that have any kindness, or <hi>passion</hi> for us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:41744:11"/>
               <head>SECT. X.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE are represented as <hi>Enemies</hi> to the Government, and tradu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as <hi>illoyal</hi> to our Prince. 'Tis suggested that we have an aversation for <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and that we have a mighty fondness for a <hi>Democratical Government.</hi> Whether those that first reported these things concerning us, did <hi>believe</hi> them we cannot tell, but we are sure that <hi>many</hi> others do. We find that precept of <hi>Machianil</hi> verified in our <hi>selves, Calumniare audacter, saltem aliquid adherebit.</hi> Calumniate bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, something at least will strike. The most pucid <hi>Lies</hi> will find some per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that will <hi>believe</hi> them; and the most improbable <hi>falshods</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive entertainment with <hi>easie</hi> and <hi>credulous</hi> minds.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By this means we are made <hi>odious</hi> to some <hi>persons,</hi> and <hi>suspected</hi> of many others; some <hi>hate</hi> us implacably, others grow <hi>jealous,</hi> and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain hard <hi>thoughts</hi> of us. Were the <hi>characters</hi> they give us <hi>true</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, we should have no <hi>reason to complain,</hi> but for as much as we know our selves <hi>innocent,</hi> it cannot but be matter of <hi>resentment</hi> to us, to be so villanously and <hi>spitefully</hi> bely'd and defamed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis true, there be <hi>very many</hi> that have other <hi>apprehensions</hi> of us, they are better <hi>acquainted</hi> with our <hi>Judgments</hi> and <hi>Lives,</hi> than to believe such odious <hi>characters</hi> and <hi>descriptions,</hi> and we have reason to <hi>bless God</hi> for it, for if all (I mean all <hi>Church-of-England-men</hi>) believed them, we must certainly be <hi>outraged</hi> in the streets, and <hi>knocked</hi> on the <hi>head</hi> in the <hi>High-wayes</hi> and <hi>Villages;</hi> and all that killed us, would think they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served a <hi>compensation</hi> for ridding the <hi>Nation</hi> of such <hi>pernicious</hi> vermin.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To these <hi>infamous lies</hi> and <hi>hellish insinuations,</hi> we must impute the with-drawing of his <hi>Majesties</hi> favour from us, for although we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he knows little of those <hi>severities</hi> that are used and exercised toward us, yet we cannot but <hi>think,</hi> that he hath a little loosned the <hi>rein,</hi> by which he restrained his <hi>Magistrates</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> from prosecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and afflicting us. We complain not of our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> we have had much <hi>experience</hi> of his clemency. He must see by other mens <hi>Eyes,</hi> and hear by other mens <hi>Ears,</hi> and if the same <hi>impious slanders</hi> be reported to him, that are to many of his <hi>subjects</hi> concerning us, (of which there is no doubt) we cannot much <hi>wonder</hi> at our present <hi>sufferings;</hi> for sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing them true, they were no more than we had <hi>abundantly</hi> deserved.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:41744:11"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> The Dissenters Expostulations.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AND what now are our Faults and Crimes, or of what number and nature are our Transactions? What is it we have done, to make us become the Objects of all that rage and wrath, that is used, and spent against us? Are we the vilest of Mortals? Are we the most profligate of Mankind? Are we the only part of the Nation, that deserve the publick Vengeance? Why are we hunted and prosecuted like Beasts of Prey, and as if we were a common Nusance to the Countrey, and Land of our Nativity or Birth.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are treated as the Off-scouring of the Earth, the filth of the World, and Refuse of the People. There is no Contempt, no Scorn, no Reproach, no Penalties, no Violence, no Injury, no Oppression, thought too much to be imposed and laid upon us. But how is it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that we have deserved it? What evidence is there of those Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that may justifie these extraordinary Methods of proceeding against us. The Christians complained of old, that they were punished and condemned for the sake of the Christian name, not for the sake of any Crimes that were proved against them, <hi>Hominis Praelium est.</hi> See <hi>Tertull.</hi> in <hi>Apolget.</hi> and <hi>Athenagoras</hi> in <hi>legat. pro Christianis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Something of this sort is happened to us in the present Age. To be a <hi>Dissenter</hi> is Crime enough to expose a man to the rage of Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. <hi>Illud solum expectatur, quod odio publico necessarium est, confessio no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis, non examinatio criminis.</hi> Dissent, to the <hi>present Establishment,</hi> is aequipollent to all the Publican and Harlot Sins in the World, and we may be guilty of them (we are sorry to speak it) at far easier and cheaper rates. Fornication, Adultery, Scandal, Oppression, Lying, Perjury, <hi>Scorn of all Religion,</hi> and Blasphemy, are <hi>Peccadilio</hi>'s in comparison of <hi>Nonconformisty.</hi> The former are easily expiated, but nothing will allow for the latter but our ruine.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:41744:12"/>4. The <hi>Christians</hi> of the first Ages did not deny that they were accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed of sundry <hi>monstrous</hi> Crimes, nor do we deny that we are made suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently vile by charge and imputation, but nothing was proved against them. Nor are those <hi>infamous</hi> Stories reported concerning us, capable of any proof or demonstration, for Lies can never become truth, nor falshoods obtain the nature of undoubted Verities, and 'tis truth alone that is proveable by argument and convictive evidence. 'Tis true we do confess, that Men of <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Wit</hi> will very finely dress a Falshood, and persons of an <hi>impudent Frent</hi> and <hi>prostituted Conscience</hi> will affirm the most <hi>prodigious</hi> Lies and Slanders; but when all is done, the nature of things and Facts is the same, and utterly invariable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 2.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Is it a Sin of so monstrous a nature, that nothing can expiate it but our destruction to refuse to subscribe Propositions of doubtful and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain nature? If they be doubtful, why are we obliged to assert their truth? If they be uncertain, why must we aver them past all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versy and Dispute? If they be neither doubtful, nor uncertain, why is it that <hi>Christians</hi> are not agreed concerning them? Why is the learned World so much divided about them? Would they everlastingly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, about things evident and apparent? Would they perpetuate a Controversy about things as plain as the Light, and obvious as the mid-day Sun?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is it a Crime that deserves all this Cruelty, and all those Barbarities that are executed upon us, that we refuse our Subscription to things of impertinent and unnecessary nature? Are all those Propositions and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things to which our Subscription and Consent, and many others, is required necessary, and of the essence of the Religion of <hi>Christ Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus?</hi> May not a man be a good Christion, though he should not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand, nor believe any thing of them? If they be necessary, why are they not comprehended in the <hi>Baptismal Covenant,</hi> or in the Creed, Lord's Prayer, and the ten Commandments? These were anciently thought to contain all the necessary Doctrines of Christian Faith and Practice, and we are of Opinion they do so still. The <hi>essential</hi> and neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary parts of Religion are invariable, they are the same <hi>now</hi> that they were in the days of the <hi>Apostles</hi> and antient Churches.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Is it so heinous a Transgression to refuse the practice of things of no use, and to no edifiacation, that no compensation can be made for it, but what will undoe us? We do not know of what use those Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:41744:12"/> are, that have been, and still are in use in this <hi>Church,</hi> nor who is edified by them. We are sure those that are the greatest <hi>Zealots</hi> for them, do not appear to be much edified by the Appointments and Insti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of God, and 'twere strange if they should be advantaged by those of Man, who are little or nothing believed by those of God. And if those that love and admire them, make no <hi>profitable</hi> use of them, What may be hoped from those that love them not?</p>
               <p n="4">4. Are not the Laws of God sufficient for our Observation? And may not Christians go safe to Heaven, under the direction, and in the Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his Commandments? Are God's Laws sufficient for their end, or are they not? If they be sufficient, What need is there of any additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to them? If they be not sufficient, Why do we assert and prove it against the <hi>Papists?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Since <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> hath freed us from the <hi>Yoke,</hi> that God himself had imposed upon the <hi>Jewish</hi> Church, we know no Obligation lying upon us, to receive a <hi>Yoke</hi> that shall be imposed upon us by Man. We refuse Obedience to none of the Laws of God, nor to no Laws of Men, that are necessary for the observance of the Divine Appointments and Institutions, such as are the determination of time and place, and sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry others, but these Laws that are the effects of <hi>pure will,</hi> and of no use nor profit, but occasions of Strife and Contention, we do profess to all the World, we know not the Obligation of them.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Must we be Ruined, Banished, or Hanged, for no other reason, but because we are loath to be damned? St. <hi>Paul</hi> saith, that <hi>Whatsoever is not of Faith is Sin, and he that doubteth is damned if he eat.</hi> We have considered the <hi>impositions</hi> that are laid upon our Judgments and Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we have spent much time in the <hi>meditation</hi> of them, and would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry willingly have submitted to them, if we could have done it with a satisfied and assured Mind. But upon the most <hi>serious deliberation</hi> which we have made upon them, we find an <hi>everlasting</hi> renitency of Judgment and Conscience against them. This is our Case, and this is our Fault, and must we abjure the Land, or swing in a Rope at home, for the sake of it? This in our <hi>Apprehension</hi> is somewhat severe, but the choice is not difficult, we had far rather be Banished our Countrey then that out of Heaven, 'tis more eligible to climb a Gallows, or ascend a Gibbet, then descend the nethermost Hell. But whether it be justifiable to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose such a choice upon us, is worthy the consideration of those that are concerned therein.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:41744:13"/>
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Is it a greater Sin to Worship God by other rules, then those pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scribed by our Laws, then it is to live as without <hi>God in the World,</hi> and never perform <hi>any publick Worship</hi> to him at all? How many thousands are there in the Towns, Cities, and Villages, of this Nation, that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attend the house of God, that never <hi>Sanctifie his Sabbaths, or Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate his Sanctuaries?</hi> And what are the Punishments that they do <hi>su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain</hi> thereby? Are they <hi>prosecuted</hi> at <hi>Law?</hi> Are their Goods seized? Their Persons Imprisoned, and their Families beggered in revenge thereof?</p>
               <p n="2">2. We hear of no Complaints or Lamentations, made by these kind of People, which surely they would do, if they had any occasion or foundation for them. They are not Men of such tame and passive Spirits, as to endure scourging without any Groans or Exclamations; for though they regard not God nor his Worship, they love their <hi>Liberty</hi> and their <hi>Estates,</hi> and would not part with them without loud signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of their Reluctancy against it. Since they cry not out of Violence and Oppression, we may be sure they are at rest.</p>
               <p n="3">3. May Men be <hi>Atheists, Infidels,</hi> or <hi>Heathens,</hi> with Impunity? May they defie God and all the Laws and Methods of his Worship with all the security they can desire or wish? And must the <hi>Dissenters</hi> be worried like <hi>Bears,</hi> and torn with Doggs because they fear God and call upon his name? 'Tis true, they do not do it altogether according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of our Laws. But do they not do it according to the Laws of God? Did St. <hi>Peter</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> use any more Ceremony or Liturgy in Preaching, Praying, and Administring the Sacrament then they do? And why may not that suffice? Is it a pardonable Crime to be a <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then,</hi> and is it a fault worthy of the severest Punishment to Worship God and his Christ after the manner and example of the Apostles? Some Men seem to be of that Opinion, but we think it were not amiss to renounce it, for sure we are, that the Devil is the Author of it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We are not ignorant of what is said, by the Masters and Fautors of Impositions, on the behalf, and for the defence of them. 'Tis said, that without them no Peace nor Order can ever be preserved in the Church of God. But we are of another mind. In our Judgment, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ought to be imposed, but a few, plain, necessary things, and those are enough for the <hi>maintenance</hi> of Peace, and that to impose a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of things, <hi>needless, obscure, controverted,</hi> and <hi>uncertain</hi> is the high
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:41744:13"/> and certain way to endless <hi>Factions▪</hi> and <hi>Divisions,</hi> and that as much peace as the Church of God is capable of in this imperfect State, may be more safely and advantageously obtain'd without them; But for this we must again refer the Reader, to the Book call'd the <hi>Samaritan.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Have we ever refused to contribute to the <hi>maintenance</hi> of the Government with our Lives and Fortunes? Have not our <hi>Purses</hi> been as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en, and our <hi>Hands</hi> as ready to defend his <hi>Majesties</hi> Honor and Greatness as any other of his Subjects? Did we ever betray any Trust that was commited to us? Have we turned our Backs in the day of Battel? Have we not been as <hi>prodigal</hi> of our Blood, and given as good Proofs of our <hi>Courage</hi> and Valour as any others that have been engaged with us in the same hazards and dangers? When, and where did we do any thing unworthy of <hi>Engish</hi> men, or good Subjects? Where are our Accusers? Let them stand forth and convince us (if they are able) of any <hi>Disloyalty,</hi> or neglect of Duty, towards the Support of the just Grandeur of our Prince.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Let them not object to us the <hi>Rebellion</hi> and <hi>Miscarriages</hi> of the last Age: We neither promoted nor approved them. Many of us were not then born; others were <hi>children;</hi> others opposed what was then done; and some that were too much guilty in the <hi>Tragedies</hi> of those times, have since <hi>repented it in Dust and Ashes.</hi> As we do not justifie, so we will not account for other mens Sins. We only plead our <hi>own Cause,</hi> and assert our own Integrity and Uprightness. We hope we shall not be punished for the <hi>Iniquities of our Fathers,</hi> nor reckoned Enemies to the State, because <hi>some of them</hi> were so.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If we must be reputed ill Subjects, because some men will suspect us, and esteemed <hi>Traytors,</hi> because <hi>poysonous Tongues</hi> will calumniate and <hi>reproach</hi> us, our Case is pityable; but without <hi>Remedy.</hi> For there is no defence against <hi>Slander;</hi> Mens Lusts, and spiteful passions are not under our <hi>Government</hi> or <hi>Restraint;</hi> what they suggest will be spoken, though never so false and infamous, and we cannot prevent it. The most unblemished <hi>Loyalty</hi> is no Protection against a <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious malignant</hi> Mind; a Tongue set on <hi>Fire of Hell,</hi> will blast the <hi>fairest</hi> and most unspotted <hi>Reputation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. We have a <hi>Province</hi> that is not easily managed to the <hi>satisfaction</hi> of these Revilers: If we refuse the <hi>Oaths, Subscriptions</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> that are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us as <hi>Testimonies</hi> and <hi>Securities</hi> of our Fidelity, we are reported and said to reject them, because they are inconsistent with our Purposes and Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Rebellion. If we accept and submit to them in the same Sence that all sober and considering Church of <hi>England</hi> men do, 'tis said that we do it with design to get <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Preferments</hi> in Church and State, that we may be the more capable of subverting and <hi>destroying</hi> both one and the other. This is the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> of multitudes of Books and Pamphlets which the Press voids every day.</p>
               <p n="5">5. What shall we do to please these Men? We are willing to give them all <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable</hi> Content; but if neither <hi>assent</hi> nor <hi>dissent</hi> to their <hi>Impositions;</hi> if neither <hi>obedience,</hi> nor <hi>disobedience</hi> to their <hi>Injunctions,</hi> will humor or please them, we must desire them to inform us what will: For we are not very well able to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form our selves.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And yet after some Consideration, we think we may have <hi>found</hi> what may
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:41744:14"/>
                  <hi>please</hi> and put them in good <hi>humour:</hi> Would we <hi>hang, drown,</hi> or <hi>cut</hi> our own <hi>Throats,</hi> and leave them Heirs to our Estates and Fortunes, 'tis not improbable but that it might be an <hi>Adventure</hi> much to their Acceptation: But if nothing else will commend us to their Favor, we must beg their Pardon, we shall not purchase it at their Price. We have no mind to be <hi>damned,</hi> to give them <hi>Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction:</hi> If they will buy it at that Rate, we must bear it; but they must excuse us, we will have no hand or part with them therein: If we must die to gratifie them, they must be our <hi>Executioners.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 5.</head>
               <p n="1">1. But what indeed is the Ground of Provocation? Are we useless, unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, or burthensom <hi>Members</hi> of the Nation? Do we live without Labour, or do we eat of the <hi>Sweat</hi> of other mens Brows? Are we not equally industrious with any other sort of men? Do we not contribute to the <hi>enriching</hi> of our <hi>Country</hi> as much as other of his <hi>Majesties</hi> Subjects? We bear our part in that <hi>Trade,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o'l in those Arts and Mysteries, by which Supplies are made to the <hi>Pleasures, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities,</hi> and <hi>Magnificence</hi> of all Orders and Degrees of men.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Do not we assist to the Advancement of the Customs and Revenues of the Crown? All men that know any thing of those matters, do acknowledge, that of <hi>late years</hi> they have received very great <hi>Emoluments,</hi> and are swollen beyond the <hi>proportion</hi> of former Ages; and have we had no <hi>part,</hi> nor share therein? Do not we partake in that Trade and Merchandise by which they are encreased and advanced?</p>
               <p n="3">3. No man of <hi>Sence</hi> can deny us a part in those Advantages, that have been made to the <hi>Revenue,</hi> and riches of our <hi>Sovereign.</hi> We have surely done something, towards the Augmentation of them, and those that deny it are such, as have neither <hi>Brains,</hi> nor Front. They are both ignorant, and themselves Impostors. And 'tis our Opinion, that those that counsel and advise our Ruine, will not be able to <hi>countervail the King's Damage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. We mention not these things out of Vanity or Ostentation; but that it may appear, that we are not utterly <hi>useless</hi> and of no signification in the world. Our Enemies report us not only <hi>unprofitable,</hi> but noxious and hurtful to the <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> The <hi>Paragraphs</hi> of this Section are a sufficient <hi>Confutation</hi> of the former of these <hi>Fables,</hi> and the whole Body of this <hi>Discourse</hi> will confute the latter to all impartial and <hi>unprejudiced</hi> Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT, 6.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Are we only a <hi>handful</hi> of Men that may all safely be destroyed? Will the Nation be of <hi>equal</hi> Strength when we are sacrificed to the Rage and Lust of those that <hi>hate</hi> us? Hath his Majesty too many Subjects; and will he be as great and <hi>puissant</hi> without, as with the Assistance of our <hi>Numbers?</hi> What our Numbers are, we do not <hi>pretend</hi> to know; but some there are scattered to and fro in most of the Towns, Cities, and Villages of the Nation, and we think more, then can with security be ruined and destroyed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis not impossible, but that His <hi>Majesty</hi> may have use for all his <hi>Subjects,</hi> were they much more <hi>numerous</hi> then they are. He is <hi>Neighbour</hi> to an <hi>Aspiring Prince,</hi> that may, in due time, give him <hi>disturbance,</hi> and if (as most certain it is) the multitude of People be the first Riches of any Nation, especially of such
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:41744:14"/> as are sober, frugal, Industrious and naturally inclin'd to <hi>Trade</hi> and <hi>Manufacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> (Epithets and Qualifications we think as justly belonging to <hi>us</hi> at least as any of our fellow Subjects.) We are not Eagle-ey'd enough to penetrate into their Politicks that contrive our Ruine; Nor can we foresee what Advantage would accrue to the King or Kingdom either in wealth or strength if at least <hi>a Million</hi> of it's most <hi>laborious Inhabitants</hi> should be forc'd either to fly into for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign parts; or be rendred by Jailing and other severe Prosecutions unuseful at home.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <p>And what will you do with your <hi>Estates</hi> when we are ruined and undone? Have you too many <hi>Tenants</hi> to occupy and employ your <hi>Lands?</hi> Where are those <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumeraries?</hi> How may we find their Residence and <hi>Habitations?</hi> If they be so <hi>numerous,</hi> how comes it to pass that so many <hi>Estates</hi> lie almost <hi>waste,</hi> and so many <hi>Houses</hi> without any <hi>Inhabitants?</hi> How is it that <hi>Farms</hi> go a begging, and that those that own them are <hi>glad</hi> to be rid of them almost upon any Terms in the World?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Are not the <hi>Rents</hi> and <hi>Values</hi> of your Lands very much <hi>diminished</hi> and abated? Are they not sunk twenty, thirty, and forty in the Hundred; and can you tell <hi>when</hi> and <hi>where</hi> they will stand? Is our <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Ruine</hi> a likely way of advancing them to their former <hi>Standard?</hi> We know not how you take your <hi>measures,</hi> nor by what Rules you make your <hi>Computations;</hi> but we are of the mind, that our <hi>Diminution</hi> will not be your <hi>Encrease;</hi> and that if we be brought to the <hi>Dung-hill,</hi> your Estates and <hi>Honours</hi> will receive no <hi>Advancement</hi> thereby.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the Value of your <hi>Lands</hi> decay, how will you support your <hi>usual</hi> State and Grandeur? How will you <hi>educate,</hi> provide for, <hi>dispose</hi> of your Children, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their <hi>Birth</hi> and <hi>Spirit?</hi> Have you not found it a work of some Care and <hi>Providence</hi> even then, when your Estates were at the highest <hi>rate</hi> and <hi>value?</hi> If it were difficult then, will it not be now <hi>impossible?</hi> Or can you do that with two thousand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> that you could not formerly do with <hi>three:</hi> will nine pence <hi>go farther than a Noble?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Are you content to be poor, so we be ruin'd; and to abate of your <hi>great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> so we may be laid on the <hi>Dunghill?</hi> Can you deny your selves some <hi>Pleasures</hi> and <hi>Satisfactions,</hi> provided we may be <hi>miserable</hi> and <hi>afflicted?</hi> Can you endure some <hi>abasement</hi> if we be trod upon as the <hi>Mire in the Streets?</hi> This is a piece of Self-Denial, which we did not expect, and we doubt whether you would do so much for the <hi>Sake of God,</hi> and all the <hi>Laws</hi> of his <hi>Gospel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 8.</head>
               <p n="1">1. In the next place, What will you do with us when we are beggared, ruined, and undone? We have so much Charity as to hope, you intend not to observe any Sanguine Methods in disposing of us. Though those that Persecute us be cruel enough, and we find it by sensible and woful experience, yet we cannot think that they intend to cut our <hi>Throats,</hi> or by short and <hi>summary Proceedings</hi> send us to our Graves. We must confess, we have known some that have said, that they could very willingly sheath their Swords in our <hi>Bowels,</hi> and bath their hands in our <hi>Blood:</hi> But we hope there are not many of this <hi>Savage</hi> and <hi>Bruitish</hi> humour.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Most <hi>Towns</hi> complain already of the <hi>number</hi> and <hi>burthen</hi> of their <hi>Poor;</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:41744:15"/> and think the charge <hi>insupportable,</hi> How then will it be born, when we are added to their <hi>number?</hi> Must we Dye, and starve of <hi>Hunger</hi> and <hi>Cold?</hi> Must we <hi>faint and swoon</hi> in the High-ways and Streets, and Villages? These are no Stories in <hi>Arras,</hi> these are no Fictions or Imageries of Fancy, If the Laws be prosecuted to the utmost, hither it will come at last.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But perhaps we may have reckoned without our <hi>Host,</hi> and made those <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions</hi> that will not be granted us. It may be we may not be <hi>permited</hi> either to <hi>live</hi> or <hi>starve</hi> at home. What then shall be done with us? Shall we be sold for <hi>Slaves,</hi> and sent to toil with <hi>Negro</hi>'s in the <hi>Western Islands?</hi> Are we a sort of <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmin</hi> fit only for their <hi>Employment and Conversation?</hi> We have read, we do confess, of Persons much better then our selves, that have been <hi>condemned</hi> to the <hi>Mines,</hi> and others to the <hi>Galleys;</hi> but those that passed those <hi>Sentences</hi> and <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> upon them, were either <hi>Heathens</hi> or <hi>Infidels.</hi> And will <hi>English Men</hi> and <hi>Protestants▪</hi> write after such Coppies, and imitate such <hi>Examples?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. And could your Eyes behold, or your Hearts endure so dismal an <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking?</hi> Could you see us <hi>shipped,</hi> and sent by <hi>thousands</hi> to the <hi>Amerian-Indies?</hi> Have you no Bowels, no P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty, nor no Compassions, for those that are of your own <hi>nature,</hi> and of the same <hi>Religion?</hi> Or could you cohibit, repress, or restrain them in so <hi>lamentable</hi> a case? What! Have you Hearts of <hi>Marble,</hi> and Entrails of <hi>Brass?</hi> Have you put off <hi>Man,</hi> and put on <hi>Beast?</hi> Have you only the Shape and Figure of Men, with the nature of <hi>Tygres, Bears</hi> and <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <p n="1">1. After this, What account then will you be able to give to God, of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verities</hi> that you exercise towards us? We hope you believe a <hi>Supream Being,</hi> and a <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y of Judgment,</hi> and that all Men must appear there, and give account of the deeds done in the <hi>Body?</hi> And do you not know that <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> is to be your <hi>Judge,</hi> and that he esteems all the Injuries and Wrongs that are done unto his Servants and <hi>Disciples,</hi> as done unto <hi>himself?</hi> And are you sure that those that you <hi>Persecute</hi> are none of them? Are you sure they are not <hi>Members of his Body, of his Flesh, and of his Bone?</hi> Do you not know <hi>that God is a Consuming Fire,</hi> and that 'tis a <hi>fearful thing to fall into his hand?</hi> These are serious Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stions, and should be seriously considered, and not scorned and turned into <hi>Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule;</hi> for if these Men, that you thus Prosecute with so much Rage and Wrath, should prove the <hi>Servants</hi> of the <hi>Living God,</hi> (as we do not doubt but that they will) <hi>Certamente no queriamos estar so Pelleio vestro,</hi> we should be very loath to be under your Skin, as the <hi>Spanish</hi> Proverb expresses it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We are not ignorant of what is pleaded in your <hi>defence,</hi> and for your justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. 'Tis said, that we are <hi>Hereticks, Schismaticks,</hi> Men of <hi>Sedition,</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verters of all <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> and many other things of like importance are charged u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on us. And were not <hi>Christ</hi> and his <hi>Apostles</hi> accused of the same <hi>Crimes?</hi> Was not <hi>Christ</hi> said to subvert the <hi>Mosaical Institution,</hi> which he denyed, by say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he came not to <hi>destroy the Law but to fulfil it?</hi> Was not <hi>Paul</hi> said to be a Turbulent Fellow, and a mover of <hi>Sedition? Were</hi> not he and others of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles and Preachers of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id to have turned the <hi>World upside down? Were</hi> not all <hi>Christians</hi> accounted <hi>Sectaries,</hi> and <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> by the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risees,</hi> and other of the People of the <hi>Jews?</hi> This <hi>Sect,</hi> say they, is <hi>every where spoken against.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:41744:15"/>3. Were they not very confident of the truth of their <hi>Opinions</hi> and <hi>Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions?</hi> Did they not think verily that <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> was a Malefactour and ought to dye? <hi>Would</hi> they have cryed out, <hi>His Blood be upon us, and upon our Children,</hi> if they had believed him <hi>inn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cent? Were</hi> not those Persons perswaded, that they h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d right on their side, which <hi>Gn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>shed their Teeth, stopped their Ears, ran upon St.</hi> Stephen, <hi>dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gged him out of the City, and stoned him with stones till he dyed? Were</hi> not the <hi>Heathens</hi> pretty well assured, in their own Conceits, that they did very commendably and well, when they outraged the <hi>Christians,</hi> and cryed out, <hi>Take away the Ʋngodly?</hi> Vid. <hi>Euseb.</hi> lib. 4. Cap. 14.</p>
               <p n="4">4. And is it not certain that they were deceived and mistaken? <hi>Was</hi> it not the Son of God, that the <hi>Jews</hi> persecuted, and murthered, as an Enemy to <hi>M ses,</hi> and a Confederate of <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elzebub? Were</hi> they not the <hi>Apostles</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of Peace, which they prosecuted as Disturbers of the Order and Government of the <hi>World? Were</hi> not the <hi>Primitive Christians,</hi> which the <hi>Heathen</hi> Prosecuted as <hi>Atheists,</hi> Impious, and Ungodly, Persons of pure and unblameable <hi>Conversa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and most Religious <hi>Worshippers</hi> of the <hi>true and onely God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And is it not possible, that you may be deceived in your Judgments a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Conceptions, concerning us? Are you not Men of like Passions and Prejudices, with those that have preceded you in past <hi>Generations?</hi> May you not have believed many Lies and slanderous Reports against us? And is not your <hi>Enmity</hi> and <hi>Ave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation</hi> towards us, raised upon impudent Falshoods, and frontless Fables? Do you know those things to be true, for the sake whereof you hate us?</p>
               <p n="6">6. 'Tis true you do know, that we do <hi>Worship</hi> God in a manner something dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from that prescribed by our Laws, and peradventure this may be all the evil that you know concerning us: 'Twas said of old, <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus vir</hi> Caius Seius, <hi>sed malus tantum quod Christianus. Caius Seius</hi> is a good Man, but he is naught, only because he is a Christian. <hi>Tertull.</hi> in <hi>Apol.</hi> And we think we might pass for honest men, were it not for our <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nconformity.</hi> And is that a Crime that will justifie all this <hi>Severity,</hi> and <hi>authorize</hi> all this <hi>Rage</hi> that is used and spent against us? we cannot tell what it may do at <hi>man's Tribunal,</hi> we do very much believe, it will not do at <hi>that of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 10.</head>
               <p n="1">1. But alas, to come up closer, what hurt do the Dissenters do indeed to the Church of <hi>England?</hi> May it not subsist and continue in its <hi>Splendor,</hi> tho' we were permitted to serve God after our <hi>own manner,</hi> in our own <hi>Congregations?</hi> Is it any hurt to a <hi>Great Lord,</hi> that there are some <hi>poor Cottages</hi> in the Neighbourhood of his <hi>Palace?</hi> Must his Stately Seat <hi>drop to the Ground,</hi> if they be suffered to stand? will the <hi>Foundations</hi> of that vast <hi>Fabrick</hi> sink, and the <hi>Walls</hi> and <hi>Roof</hi> fall to the Earth, if these remain in the Vicinage thereof? We cannot imagine how the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles</hi> can do any Injury to the <hi>magnificence</hi> of our <hi>English</hi> Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. What <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>jury</hi> did the <hi>French Church</hi> suffer by permitting <hi>Dissenting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>berty of their own <hi>Worship</hi> and Congregations? we think that <hi>Church</hi> as <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lustrious</hi> when it permitted them their <hi>Liberty,</hi> as now, when it is usi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g all <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Methods</hi> to deprive them of it. Besides, the Liberty granted to the <hi>Protestants,</hi> gave it the Reputation of some <hi>Kindness</hi> and <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nity;</hi> whereas their present <hi>Proceedings</hi> bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>st its <hi>Reputation,</hi> and expose it as <hi>cruel, barbar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> and <hi>persidi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us,</hi> to all considering and <hi>impartial</hi> men.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And we are of the mind, that Indulgence to <hi>Dissenting</hi> Churches, would be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:41744:16"/> no <hi>diminution</hi> to the Glory of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Yea, we do believe, that it would make it more <hi>illustrious,</hi> and give it a fairer <hi>Reputation</hi> than the present <hi>Persecutions</hi> will ever do. <hi>Persecution</hi> sooner or later turns to the <hi>Reproach</hi> and Infamy of those that are the <hi>Authors</hi> and <hi>Promoters</hi> of it. Whatever it may be in the <hi>Opinion</hi> of some Men in the present Age, we make no doubt but it will be <hi>odious</hi> in the next. Those that have been conversant in <hi>History,</hi> cannot but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, that <hi>Persecution</hi> hath always left a <hi>Spot</hi> and a <hi>Stain</hi> upon those that have been <hi>Agents</hi> therein; and such a one as no <hi>Soap,</hi> or <hi>Niter</hi> will ever wash out, or cleanse. <hi>Bonner</hi> and <hi>Gardner</hi> will be <hi>infamous</hi> to all Generations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 11.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Is it the matter of our Doctrine you take Offence at? Do our Ministers commend false Doctrine to those that hear them? Do they preach <hi>pernicious</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors? Is there any thing in their <hi>Sermons</hi> and Discourses that is of dangerous or mischievous Nature? They are <hi>men</hi> as well as others; and we do not doubt but they are <hi>lyable to Errors</hi> and <hi>Mistakes</hi> as well as others of Humane Race; but are their Errors of more fatal <hi>Consequence</hi> and dangerous <hi>Quality</hi> than those that are to be found among the <hi>regular</hi> and <hi>conformable</hi> Clergy? If they be so, why is it not <hi>proved</hi> against them; why are they not <hi>convinced</hi> thereof to their <hi>Reproach</hi> and Shame?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Have they indeed <hi>preached Sedition,</hi> or suggested such things as might disturb the <hi>publick Peace?</hi> Have they <hi>spoke evil of Dignities,</hi> or endeavoured to mutiny the People against them? Have they <hi>perswaded</hi> them to cast off the <hi>Yoke,</hi> and assert their own <hi>Freedom,</hi> to the Overthrow of all good <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> and to the introducing of <hi>Anarchy,</hi> and utter Confusion? On the contrary, is there any Book written for Loyalty, with more Conviction, Weight of Argument, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berness of Spirit, and Perspicacity of Notion (though intricate sometimes in the Style) than that Book so honestly commended by the Bishop of <hi>Cork,</hi> Intituled <hi>A peaceable Resolution of Conscience, touching our present Impositions:</hi> And is, not the Author of that Book a <hi>Nonconformisi?</hi> we speak not of what was done some years agone; but vindicate our own <hi>Innocency:</hi> we defend not the Faults of our <hi>Progenitors;</hi> nor can we cure the Miscarriages of the <hi>Past age.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Have any of our serious Ministers published Tenents inconsistent with the Articles of our common Creed? Have they denied the God that Made them, the Saviour that Redeemed them, or the Holy-Ghost that Sanctifieth and Reformeth them? In brief, have they subverted, or denied any of the great <hi>Essentials</hi> of <hi>Christianity?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Do they not Preach the same Matters of <hi>Faith, Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> that are discoursed and perswaded by the <hi>Conformable Ministers?</hi> Do they not with equal seriousness assert the necessity of them? Do they not press <hi>Self-denial, Heavenly mindedness, Mortification, Contempt of the World, Love to God and Men,</hi> and all the Duties of <hi>Christians and Believers?</hi> And do they not do this with as much Life and Zeal, with as much Fervour and Affection as they are able; yea, and with such as comes not short of that, of any of their <hi>Conformahle Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. If these things be not true, why are we not openly confuted and shamed in the Faces of the <hi>World?</hi> If the Doctrine of our Ministers be false, and of malignant nature, why is there no proof made of it, and why are they not made justly infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thereby? But if it be true and sound, and such as is for the <hi>Edification</hi> of <hi>Christians</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Godliness,</hi> why are they and we Persecuted, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached for it?</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:41744:16"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> The Dissenters Supplications.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <p>IT is time now to come to a few modest Requests; we do in the first place <hi>humbly</hi> desire that we may be permitted the <hi>Communion</hi> of the Church, upon the <hi>terms</hi> propounded by <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> and his <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles,</hi> and exemplified in the <hi>practice</hi> of the Primitive <hi>Churches</hi> and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians: St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls the Church <hi>The House of God;</hi> and the Author of the <hi>Epistle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> speaking of <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> calls it his <hi>own House,</hi> and 'tis our Opinion that it belongs <hi>to God</hi> and his <hi>Christ</hi> to appoint the <hi>Conditions</hi> and <hi>Qualifications</hi> of Admission; and we do <hi>humbly conceive</hi> that they have done it, and that the <hi>Stewards</hi> of their House have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do to <hi>alter</hi> them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We do not find <hi>that God,</hi> and his <hi>Son,</hi> and the holy <hi>Apostles</hi> inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and directed by <hi>his Spirit,</hi> ever required any of <hi>those things</hi> in order to Church <hi>Communion</hi> which are demanded of us, and for the <hi>refusal</hi> whereof we are shut out and <hi>excluded</hi> from it, and prosecuted with so much <hi>severity</hi> besides: For ought that we can perceive, their <hi>Conditions of Communion</hi> were only a <hi>few, plain, necessary</hi> things; we can observe no numerous <hi>Articles</hi> of dark, unnecessary and <hi>uncertain</hi> nature, ever proposed to those that became Converts to the <hi>Christian Religion: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and be Baptized,</hi> sayes St. <hi>Peter,</hi> Act. 2.38. <hi>If thou believest thou may'st be Baptized,</hi> sayes <hi>Philip</hi> to the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> Act. 8.37.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The altering <hi>Gods terms</hi> of Communion hath broken the Peace of the <hi>Church,</hi> split it in pieces, and run it into <hi>Factions, Parties</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visions</hi> well nigh these <hi>Fourteen hundred years;</hi> and that <hi>blessed</hi> Engine that first tore it in <hi>pieces,</hi> keeps the <hi>Wounds</hi> of it open, and hinders all <hi>coalition</hi> of the parts of it to this day; and although the thing be <hi>sufficiently</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, and hath been said and repeated by many <hi>great Divines,</hi> and other very <hi>learned</hi> men, yet those that are <hi>concerned</hi> to know it, neither <hi>cannot</hi> or <hi>will not</hi> see it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nothing will ever heal the <hi>Breaches</hi> of <hi>Christendom,</hi> or make up those <hi>rents</hi> and <hi>divisions</hi> that are therein, but the removal of the <hi>Causes</hi> of them, among which we reckon this the most <hi>principal,</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:41744:17"/> most <hi>mischievous;</hi> all other means do but exasperate the <hi>feuds</hi> and <hi>animosities</hi> that are among <hi>Christians</hi> and <hi>Churches,</hi> or else destroy all true <hi>Religion, Piety,</hi> and <hi>serious Godliness,</hi> (which is the <hi>glory</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Churches) under pretence of preserving the <hi>Peace</hi> of them: <hi>Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinem faciunt, &amp; pacem vocant;</hi> saith <hi>Tertull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. The reducing the <hi>terms of Communion</hi> to their primitive <hi>Purity, Plainness,</hi> and <hi>Simplicity,</hi> would put an end to almost all the <hi>unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral</hi> Heats, Separations and divisions that are in the <hi>Church of England:</hi> This would bring almost all the <hi>Dissenters</hi> into its Communion, and for others, <hi>provisions</hi> might be made to their <hi>satisfaction,</hi> upon such terms as will not <hi>prejudice</hi> but honour this <hi>Church,</hi> and give it the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of a very <hi>Humane, Tender</hi> and <hi>Christian</hi> temper.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And why we may not be <hi>Christians,</hi> and enjoy the Communion of <hi>Christians</hi> upon the good <hi>old terms,</hi> we do confess we are somewhat to seek, and we are able to give our <hi>selves</hi> no other <hi>account</hi> of it, but that it is not the <hi>good pleasure</hi> of the Devil and his <hi>Agents and Factors:</hi> We do conceive that God <hi>Almighty</hi> hath made no change in the <hi>Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> of admission into his <hi>Family</hi> and House; those that do affirm it, are obliged to <hi>prove</hi> it, which we think will be a very <hi>difficult province.</hi> If God himself hath not <hi>altered</hi> them, we cannot tell who should be <hi>so bold</hi> to attempt it, unless it be that great <hi>enemy</hi> of God, and some others that do <hi>receive direction</hi> from him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <p n="1">1. If the terms of <hi>Communion</hi> may not be altered, we pray that there be such a <hi>sense of Savour</hi> put upon them, as may make us <hi>capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> of consenting to them, and that <hi>that</hi> sense be declared by <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or by the <hi>Judges</hi> of the Land, that so there may remain no <hi>scruple</hi> concerning it; this would satisfie the <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealousies</hi> of our Consciences: The opinion of some <hi>private</hi> persons <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately</hi> delivered, though they may be <hi>great</hi> men, and give <hi>great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> for it, will not satisfie us; we speak it from <hi>experience,</hi> we have <hi>heard</hi> and read what hath been <hi>said</hi> on the behalf of such an <hi>Expositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as we could acknowledge and <hi>assent</hi> unto, but when all is done, our <hi>Judgments</hi> are not at rest in the <hi>determination</hi> of one or two pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable <hi>Doctors</hi> or Expositors.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We do not desire by any <hi>Exposition</hi> of the imposed <hi>Oaths, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scriptions</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> to be discharged from any part of the <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:41744:17"/> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> we owe to our King, we desire not to be freed of any <hi>obligation</hi> that God hath laid upon us; nay, we do <hi>suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciently understand</hi> that 'tis impossible: No humane <hi>Interpretation</hi> can weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en or dissolve the <hi>force</hi> of the divine <hi>Laws;</hi> we are willing to give to <hi>Caesar the things which are Caesar</hi>'s, and we are willing to <hi>oblige</hi> our selves thereunto; our Judgment concerning the Power of <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> and the Duty of <hi>Subjects,</hi> we desire the Reader to receive from Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Second Plea, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3, 4, and 5. and a Book before named.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Nor is it our wish or <hi>Intention</hi> by any <hi>Exposition</hi> to be left at <hi>Liberty</hi> to subvert the Fundamentals of <hi>Christian</hi> Religion, or to revile the <hi>Articles, Liturgy</hi> or <hi>Discipline</hi> of the Church; there are many <hi>things</hi> that we can <hi>endure,</hi> that we cannot <hi>approve,</hi> and may we have the <hi>Liberty</hi> of our own <hi>Judgments,</hi> we can quietly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to others the <hi>Liberty</hi> of theirs; we will maintain no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversies about differing <hi>Opinions</hi> in things of no great <hi>moment,</hi> and such as are of <hi>obscure</hi> and <hi>uncertain nature</hi> and truth; in <hi>such things</hi> let men think as they list, and we will do so too; we will not break the <hi>peace</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> for the sake of them; but the <hi>imposing</hi> these things upon our <hi>Faith,</hi> and obliging us to avow them of <hi>equal truth</hi> with the <hi>Word of God,</hi> is, and we think ought to be an <hi>abomination:</hi> We know no <hi>medium</hi> between <hi>truth</hi> and falshood, nor doth truth receive <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus,</hi> all truth is equally true; what is <hi>not contrary to the Word</hi> of God (they are the words in which we are to subscribe to the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> and Book of <hi>Ordination</hi>) is <hi>agreeable</hi> thereunto; and what is <hi>agreeable</hi> thereunto, is as true as the Sacred and <hi>inspired</hi> Volumes; which (to speak <hi>modestly</hi>) is to our apprehension a very <hi>bold</hi> and <hi>daring</hi> assertion.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Such a <hi>favourable</hi> Exposition (as we have mentioned) of the <hi>things imposed</hi> and required of us, hath been several times Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the use of the <hi>Sheriffs</hi> and <hi>Citizens of London,</hi> as also by the <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Judicious</hi> Author of the <hi>Peaceable Resolution</hi> already ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; to which we will add the Author of the <hi>Peaceable Design,</hi> in his answer to Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi>'s Sermon: We think the sense of <hi>sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour</hi> put upon the <hi>impositions</hi> by these <hi>Authors,</hi> or rather <hi>Author</hi> (for we think indeed they came out of the same mint) to be the result of many <hi>thoughts,</hi> and of much <hi>consideration;</hi> and might it have publick and authentique <hi>approbation,</hi> it would heal almost all the <hi>Divisions</hi> and <hi>Separations</hi> that are among us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:41744:18"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <p n="1">1. If neither of these <hi>requests</hi> may be granted to us, we doe most <hi>humbly</hi> begg that we may be <hi>perswaded</hi> and argued into <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity</hi> by Reason and <hi>Discourses:</hi> We are <hi>Men,</hi> and Reason is of our <hi>Essence</hi> and Constitution; we are willing to be <hi>governed</hi> and directed by it, and we do say, (that though what hath been <hi>said</hi> hitherunto in the <hi>justification</hi> of it, doth not satisfie our <hi>Conscien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> nor take off our <hi>objections</hi> against it) we are much more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by your arguments than by your <hi>Clubs:</hi> We do plainly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that 'tis sound <hi>reason</hi> with some little <hi>intermixtures</hi> of kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and love, that must make us <hi>Proselytes</hi> to the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> or nothing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To perswade us to <hi>Conformity</hi> by Prisons and <hi>Consiscations,</hi> is, in our apprehension, something like demonstrating a Proposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Euclide,</hi> or <hi>Apologizing</hi> by a <hi>Beetle</hi> and <hi>Wedges,</hi> and we think they will equally produce their effects. When any <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matician</hi> shall do the one, the <hi>Church of England</hi> may perform the other; We never find our selves Edified by a <hi>Dungeon,</hi> or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed by the <hi>spoyling of our Goods: Force hath as little power on Souls, as a Chyrurgeons Knife on the Ʋnderstanding and Affections of men; Remedies must have some Analogy with the Sick, and their Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eases; Force prevails upon the Body, and Reason upon the Soul,</hi> Du Plessis in his Memoires, <hi>vol.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 562.</p>
               <p n="3">3. These <hi>barbarous</hi> methods of <hi>Instruction,</hi> instead of bringing us <hi>nearer</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> set us at a <hi>greater distance</hi> from it: <hi>Who can better judge of the inutility of force in the business of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than your Majesty;</hi> (saith Du Plessis, <hi>ubi supra.) You have employed your arms with success against such as they were designed to ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, but have made no other advantage thereby than to learn, that the greatest successes are not successeful against the Consciences of men.</hi> See his Letter to <hi>Henry</hi> the Third of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. 'Tis not impossible but that your <hi>Severities</hi> may bring some of us to your <hi>Churches,</hi> but do you think they will alter our <hi>Judgments,</hi> or reconcile us to your <hi>way</hi> and <hi>method</hi> of Serving God? Do you think you have made us <hi>Converts</hi> to your <hi>Liturgy</hi> and <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> when you have <hi>basted</hi> us into your <hi>Assemblies</hi> and <hi>Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations?</hi> If you think so, you are very much <hi>mistaken;</hi> we have no <hi>other,</hi> nor no <hi>better</hi> thoughts of it than we had <hi>before.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:41744:18"/>5. Many of us do think it <hi>lawful</hi> to communicate in your <hi>As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semblies</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> when we are <hi>permitted</hi> no <hi>other</hi> nor no <hi>bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> we can be <hi>contented</hi> with mean <hi>Provisions</hi> and <hi>Lodging</hi> in our Travails, and where no <hi>better</hi> is to be had, but where there is <hi>Liberty</hi> and Choice, we do usually <hi>choose the best,</hi> and we hope we are not to be <hi>blamed</hi> for it; we speak not this to <hi>disparage</hi> the publique <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Worship,</hi> that hath the <hi>approbation</hi> of the Government and <hi>Laws:</hi> We do <hi>acknowledge</hi> that there are many <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>excellent</hi> Persons that serve at the publick <hi>Altars,</hi> and if <hi>all</hi> or <hi>most</hi> were so, we should have much less <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity</hi> of going elsewhere; but alas it is not so, and they must be very <hi>ignorant</hi> or very <hi>partial</hi> that can deny it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Besides, in our Opinion, that is <hi>best</hi> that does us <hi>most good,</hi> and is most accommodate to our <hi>Capacities,</hi> and we find a <hi>plain Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course</hi> makes deeper <hi>Impressions</hi> upon our Hearts, and moves and <hi>enlivens</hi> our Passions and <hi>Affections,</hi> much more than a <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>elaborate Oration:</hi> Plain Countrey People like the <hi>mean Provisions</hi> of their own <hi>Cottages</hi> better than the more <hi>costly</hi> Accomodations of <hi>Palaces</hi> and <hi>Courts;</hi> 'Tis not what is best in it <hi>self,</hi> but what is best <hi>for us,</hi> that we <hi>love</hi> and <hi>chuse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. And as <hi>many,</hi> yea, far the <hi>most</hi> of us come to your <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations</hi> with the liking and <hi>approbation</hi> of our Judgments and <hi>Consciences,</hi> so 'tis very possible that some may be <hi>affrighted</hi> thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>Warrants, Constables</hi> and <hi>Informers,</hi> something to the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gret, trouble</hi> and <hi>offence</hi> of them; but surely <hi>these</hi> are no more in <hi>love</hi> with your <hi>Communion,</hi> than the <hi>Protestants</hi> in <hi>France</hi> are in love with that Worship to which they are forced with <hi>Pitch-forks,</hi> and dragged with <hi>Ropes:</hi> But peradventure so we come to your <hi>Churches,</hi> 'tis indifferent to you whether it be <hi>with or against our Judgments,</hi> whether it be out of <hi>Love</hi> or out of <hi>Fear,</hi> out of <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son</hi> or out of <hi>Interest,</hi> to serve <hi>God</hi> or escape the <hi>Gallowes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. This was not the ancient <hi>Method</hi> of Converting and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing men into the <hi>Christian</hi> Communion, we do not find it either <hi>prescribed</hi> or practised by <hi>Christ</hi> or his <hi>Apostles,</hi> or any of the Primitive <hi>Bishops:</hi> We are afraid this <hi>new Invention</hi> is something <hi>diabolical;</hi> if you can Proselyte us by <hi>Gods wayes</hi> and means of <hi>Conversion,</hi> do it with all our <hi>hearts;</hi> but <hi>Sathanical</hi> endeavours will not encrease your <hi>Communion,</hi> nor add to the numbers of your <hi>Churches,</hi> unless you will reckon them your <hi>Members</hi> and <hi>Brethren,</hi> that are no otherwise such, than <hi>Christian Slaves</hi> are the <hi>Subjects</hi> of the <hi>Great Turk,</hi> or King of <hi>Morocco:</hi> Christ <hi>Jesus</hi> would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive none but <hi>willing</hi> Servants into his <hi>Family,</hi> but those that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:41744:19"/> to be his <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Stewards,</hi> receive, yea, force in the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing,</hi> so they do in <hi>France,</hi> and so they do <hi>somewhere</hi> else, or we are <hi>shrewdly</hi> mistaken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We do further <hi>intreat,</hi> that such of us as cannot by <hi>reason</hi> and <hi>argument</hi> be brought into your <hi>Communion,</hi> may have the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to go our <hi>own</hi> way to <hi>Heaven;</hi> we do readily <hi>grant</hi> that there is but <hi>one way</hi> thither; <hi>I am the way, the truth and the life, no man comes to the Father but by me,</hi> saith Christ Jesus; <hi>There is no name under Heaven given unto men, whereby they may be saved, but the name of Jesus of Nazareth,</hi> saith the Apostle; nor do we pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any other way, but by <hi>Christ Jesus,</hi> nor other Conditions, but <hi>Faith, Repentance</hi> and sincere <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Gospel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. But thô the <hi>way to Heaven</hi> be but <hi>one,</hi> and the great <hi>essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> duties of <hi>Religion</hi> be the same <hi>to all,</hi> and have the same <hi>obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon all,</hi> yet the <hi>manner</hi> of performing them may be <hi>various,</hi> and very much of the <hi>Controversie,</hi> and many of the <hi>Divisions</hi> that are among <hi>Christians</hi> derive from thence: We are all obliged to make our <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Supplications</hi> to God, but it may be <hi>done</hi> by a <hi>form,</hi> or by extemporate <hi>conceptions;</hi> all that are admitted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Communion</hi> of Gods Church, are obliged to be Baptized at their <hi>admission,</hi> but this <hi>Sacrament</hi> may be administred just ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Institution</hi> of Christ, and practice of his <hi>Apostles,</hi> (which is surely much the better way) or with some <hi>appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dages</hi> and humane <hi>Inventions:</hi> All Church-members are obliged to <hi>examine themselves,</hi> and partake in <hi>the Body</hi> and <hi>Blood of our Lord:</hi> The Sacramental <hi>Elements</hi> may be given them either <hi>Kneeling, Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>Sitting,</hi> and in leavened or <hi>unleavened</hi> Bread. Many other <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties</hi> might be observed in the <hi>manner</hi> of performing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Duties</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> but to avoid <hi>prolixity,</hi> we shall pretermit and pass them over.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the <hi>Modes</hi> of performing our <hi>publick</hi> Duties and <hi>Worship</hi> to God, we do <hi>humbly</hi> begg we may have our <hi>Liberty:</hi> Where God hath <hi>bound</hi> us, we desire no <hi>liberty,</hi> where God hath left us at <hi>large,</hi> we <hi>desire</hi> we may not be <hi>restrained;</hi> if any <hi>accident</hi> or combination of <hi>accidents</hi> shall make the <hi>restraint</hi> of our Liberty <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary,</hi> we shall submit to such <hi>restraint;</hi> but where there is no
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:41744:19"/>
                  <hi>necessity</hi> of it, we know no <hi>obligation</hi> lying upon us to <hi>resign</hi> it, or bring our selves into <hi>bondage:</hi> Were the <hi>Rulers</hi> of the Church the absolute <hi>Lords</hi> of it, we should make their <hi>Wills</hi> the measure of our <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience;</hi> but since they are but <hi>Stewards,</hi> we shall obey them when they commend to us the <hi>Laws</hi> of God, and in other things when they give us <hi>good reason</hi> for it; but in things that have no <hi>reason</hi> to justifie, but many to <hi>condemn</hi> them, we hope they will have us excused.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We shall take no <hi>Liberty</hi> to reproach the established <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> or any of those that do <hi>attend</hi> it: We shall Serve and <hi>Worship</hi> God after our own <hi>manner,</hi> and rejoice in such <hi>Liberty</hi> and Permission, but shall not meddle with, much less <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame</hi> that of the publick <hi>Congregations:</hi> We do believe there are many <hi>good Christians</hi> that live in the Communion of the Parish <hi>Churches,</hi> and we would do so too, could we have <hi>Ministers</hi> of to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable <hi>sufficiency,</hi> and could we satisfie the scruples of our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences</hi> concerning the <hi>Lawfulness</hi> of it. Would they retain the same <hi>charitable</hi> Opinion concerning us, there might be a <hi>Ʋnity of Affection,</hi> Tranquility and <hi>Peace</hi> among us, and all the <hi>Cruelty,</hi> Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and <hi>Oppressions</hi> on the one side, and all the <hi>Complaints</hi> and Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries of <hi>Injustice</hi> and <hi>Persecution</hi> on the other, might come to a <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod,</hi> and receive a <hi>determination.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. We know you account us <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> and many <hi>Attempts</hi> have been made, and <hi>Endeavours</hi> used to prove us so, and in your <hi>apprehensions</hi> with manifest success. 'Tis not the design of these few <hi>Sheets</hi> to discuss that Controversie; all that we shall say concerning it, is only this▪ If we had departed from your Communion <hi>volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily,</hi> and for the sake of any <hi>necessary</hi> Truth or <hi>Law of God,</hi> we could not have excused our selves from that <hi>imputation;</hi> but, since yod have <hi>forced</hi> us out of it by your <hi>own Laws,</hi> and by the <hi>Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of things (if not certainly false) of doubtful and <hi>unnecessary</hi> nature, we hope you will <hi>excuse</hi> us, and take the <hi>blame</hi> upon your selves. If men may make the terms and conditions of <hi>Church-communion,</hi> Schism will be a <hi>vagrant</hi> and <hi>uncertain</hi> thing, and 'twill be <hi>impossible</hi> to fix the <hi>nature</hi> of it, or to tell wherein it <hi>consists;</hi> that may be <hi>Schism</hi> one year, that is none the next; and that may be <hi>Schism</hi> in one Church, that is none in another, and 'twill be of so <hi>lubricous</hi> and <hi>slippery</hi> a nature, that no man will be able to lay hold of it; whereas, in our Opinion, <hi>Schism</hi> is of a certain and determinate Essence, as are all other Sins.</p>
               <p n="6">6 But let it be supposed (for we will not grant) that we are <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> we hope we may be permitted to worship God in our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:41744:20"/>
                  <hi>own Congregacions,</hi> notwithstanding that <hi>supposition:</hi> We know no <hi>Law of God</hi> that will allow or justifie <hi>Church Governours</hi> in the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secution of all <hi>Schismaticks</hi> to ruine or <hi>destruction:</hi> We have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed after it, but we cannot <hi>find</hi> it either in the <hi>New Testament</hi> nor in the <hi>Old:</hi> We <hi>are Christians as well as</hi> you, <hi>we adore the same God, we seek Salvation by the same Christ, we believe the same Bible, we are the Children of the same Father, we expect a part in the same Inheritance, by the same Will and Testament.</hi> They are the words of <hi>Du Plessis</hi> in a case something like our own; Why then may we not have our liberty of serving God in our own Assemblies?</p>
               <p n="7">7. The <hi>Novations</hi> had their liberty at <hi>Rome, Alexandria, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinople,</hi> and in some parts of <hi>Phrygia.</hi> The <hi>Moletians</hi> had their liberty in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and some parts of <hi>Aegypt.</hi> The <hi>Donatists</hi> were very <hi>numerous,</hi> and very tumultuous and barbarous in <hi>Africa,</hi> as St. <hi>Austin</hi> reports them, and yet they were <hi>permitted</hi> for very many years, though reputed <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> and that deservedly too. The Protestants in <hi>France</hi> (accounted <hi>Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>smaticks</hi> by the Papists) were permitted the <hi>liberty</hi> of their own <hi>Churches</hi> till within these two or three years, and might have been so still, if the <hi>French King</hi> had not been influenced by two or three <hi>Jesuites.</hi> The like liberty they have in <hi>Poland, Helvetia,</hi> and many parts of <hi>Germany;</hi> and we hope the Church of <hi>England</hi> will be as kind to us, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is to their and our Protestant Brethren.</p>
               <p>'Tis said that <hi>Schism</hi> is a <hi>Damnable Sin,</hi> and reckoned among the <hi>works</hi> of the flesh, and that the <hi>Primitive Fathers</hi> have spoken some things against it: to which we shall only say, that we do not know that we have been proved guilty of <hi>Schism</hi> as yet, and we would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire those that thrust us out of their Communion to look at home, and when they have proved themselves <hi>innocent,</hi> let them cast <hi>Stones</hi> at us if they please. We have read, that those that cause Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations are the <hi>Schismaticks;</hi> and if so, we are <hi>afraid,</hi> that tho the Church of <hi>England</hi> may wash their hands of that charge, they will hardly be found <hi>clean.</hi> This (we think) the <hi>worthy Author</hi> of that Book called <hi>The Protestant Reconciler,</hi> hath proved beyond all contradiction.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:41744:20"/>
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <p n="1">1. But if you be immutable in the <hi>Opinion</hi> of our being dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>Schismaticks,</hi> we will make this further <hi>request</hi> unto you: Pray suffer us to inherit the <hi>fruit of our own wayes,</hi> and <hi>to be filled with our own devices.</hi> This is a <hi>Supplication</hi> that peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may look something <hi>odd,</hi> and <hi>strange,</hi> but it proceeds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your <hi>Hypothesis,</hi> not upon our own; for after <hi>the way that you call</hi> Schism, <hi>we worship the God of our Fathers, and by those wayes and methods of Devotion that you account damnable,</hi> we hope to save our Souls.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We cannot prevail with our selves to think that you have any <hi>extraordinary</hi> kindness for us: If persecuting and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting us be <hi>dumonstrations</hi> of love, we do confess we have <hi>had more of them</hi> than we have desired, but we have hitherunto looked on them as <hi>Indications</hi> of hatred; and why may we not therefore be permitted the <hi>Liberty</hi> of our Assemblies, as a means of promoting your own wishes and common Imprecations? Are you indeed unwilling of our damnation, and tender least we perish? we are glad of it if it be true, but 'twill be hard to <hi>impress upon our minds</hi> any such kind of perswasion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The favour that we have now begged, is no other than what you grant to many of your <hi>own Church:</hi> how many <hi>Conventicles</hi> of riotous <hi>Sensualists,</hi> and debauched <hi>Villains</hi> do as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble every day to serve <hi>their God,</hi> and promote their own <hi>Damnation?</hi> how numerous and frequent are the Assemblies of <hi>Drunkards, Whore-masters, Blasphemers, Atheists, Scoffers</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riders</hi> of Christ Jesus and his Gospel? and are they not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted so to do without any disturbance or <hi>molestation?</hi> what <hi>Warrants, Constables, Justices</hi> of the Peace, or Files of <hi>Musque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teers</hi> are ever employed to <hi>attacque</hi> or seize them? surely <hi>Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Whoring, Drunkenness</hi> and <hi>Blasphemy</hi> are against the <hi>Laws,</hi> as well as <hi>Praying, Preaching, Reading</hi> the Scriptures, and other Exercises of Religion; and, in our judgment as likely a way to <hi>Hell.</hi> How comes it to pass that <hi>liberty</hi> of Conscience is permitted in <hi>one case,</hi> and denyed in the <hi>other?</hi> are you willing that your own <hi>dear</hi> Brethren, and Members of your <hi>Church</hi> should go down to the <hi>infernal Pit,</hi> and are you loath that we
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:41744:21"/> that you account your <hi>Enemies</hi> should come within the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect or <hi>Neighbourhood</hi> of it? This is a strange <hi>preposterous</hi> kind of <hi>Charity,</hi> and as 'tis without Precept (for ought that we can find) so, we could be very well content, that there were no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances or <hi>Examples</hi> of it in the <hi>Practises</hi> of men.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Let us have but as much liberty to <hi>serve God,</hi> as your own good Friends have to serve <hi>the Devil,</hi> and we will ask you no more: We speak now according to our <hi>own Notions</hi> and <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions</hi> of things: We do think, that in our <hi>Congregations</hi> we do worship the great God in and through Christ Jesus, and that your Brethren in the fore-named Assemblies do serve the <hi>Devil,</hi> and we are much <hi>assured</hi> that we are not mistaken: Why this Petition should be <hi>rejected,</hi> we cannot well <hi>comprehend.</hi> Is preaching the Doctrine of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> a greater Offence to you than <hi>Blasphemy</hi> and <hi>Drunkenness?</hi> is praying to <hi>the Majesty of Heaven</hi> more nauseous to you, than <hi>Adultery</hi> and <hi>Fornication?</hi> is being at a <hi>Conventicle</hi> a greater Abomination in your eyes, than being at a <hi>Brothel-house?</hi> are you better plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed with the <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Execrations</hi> of your own Church-<hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> at their Assemblies, than with the <hi>Confessions, Prayers</hi> and <hi>Thanksgivings</hi> which are at ours? or do you think that our <hi>Worship</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> to God, will be more mischievous to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> than the Loosness, Profaneness and <hi>Abominations</hi> of your own <hi>beloved Disciples?</hi> do you imagine, that the solemn and <hi>serious</hi> devotions of our <hi>Congregations,</hi> will call louder to Heaven for <hi>vengeance,</hi> than the <hi>Bedlam</hi>-noise, and profane Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stivals and <hi>Revells</hi> of your <hi>Tavern</hi> Assemblies? your permitting <hi>liberty</hi> to the one, and laying <hi>constraint</hi> on the other, seem to import and bespeak such <hi>conceptions;</hi> but we could not think that you could give any <hi>assent</hi> unto them, had we not been told, that some men are <hi>given up to believe a lie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VI.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We pray, <hi>do by us</hi> as you would be <hi>done unto,</hi> and give us such <hi>measure</hi> as you would should be given <hi>to you,</hi> were you in our <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Case:</hi> This is no unreasonable <hi>Request,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing established upon a Precept of our Saviour. Suppose you differed no <hi>more</hi> from the <hi>Papists,</hi> than we do from <hi>you;</hi> and suppose further, that their <hi>Doctrine</hi> were the approved <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:41744:21"/> of the Countrey in which you lived, would you be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented to be persecuted to <hi>Beggery</hi> and <hi>want?</hi> would you be willing to be <hi>ruined</hi> and destroyed for such <hi>varieties</hi> and <hi>diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences?</hi> could you see your <hi>Houses</hi> broken open, and your <hi>Wives</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> affrighted to Sickness and <hi>Death?</hi> could you be dragged to <hi>Prison,</hi> and laid among <hi>Villains</hi> and <hi>Vermin,</hi> and think you were fairly and equitably dealt withall, and that you had no reason to <hi>complain?</hi> could you think such <hi>Treatment</hi> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than a just <hi>recompence</hi> of your dissent from the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and Discipline of the <hi>Church?</hi> We cannot believe that you could approve of those <hi>Rigours in your own case,</hi> which you think fit to <hi>exercise</hi> upon us without any <hi>Regrett</hi> or <hi>Remorse</hi> of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis not many years since some of you were <hi>treated</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what <hi>ruggedly</hi> for your dissent from the Methods of <hi>Worship</hi> and Systems of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Opinion</hi> countenanced by those that had usurped the Government of the Nation: 'Twas then almost as criminal to hear <hi>Common-prayer,</hi> as 'tis now to <hi>refuse</hi> it; and and to own the 39 <hi>Articles,</hi> as 'tis now to <hi>reject</hi> them; to preach <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Obedience,</hi> as 'tis now to foment <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> As we remember these things with <hi>abhorrence,</hi> so, we are sure you did bear them with great <hi>uneasiness</hi> and <hi>complaint.</hi> 'Tis true, they were <hi>Ʋsurpers</hi> that imposed upon you, and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted</hi> you, but was that all the reason of your <hi>trouble and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation?</hi> would you not have thought <hi>it hard,</hi> and <hi>intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble almost,</hi> to have been forbidden to have <hi>worshipped</hi> God by the <hi>English Liturgy,</hi> or to have kneeled at the Sacrament, or to have baptized your Children with <hi>Godfathers,</hi> and the sign of the <hi>Cross,</hi> even by lawful <hi>Governours?</hi> and would you not have <hi>complained</hi> much more if you had been prosecuted to utter ruine for these things? would you not have cryed out of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> and <hi>Oppression,</hi> of <hi>Barbarousness,</hi> Inhumanity, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercises of an <hi>Empire</hi> over the Judgments and <hi>Consciences</hi> of men? We are of the mind that these things would have pinched and been grievous, though they had been imposed by <hi>just</hi> and <hi>right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis not <hi>impossible,</hi> but that you may fall under the <hi>Roman Yoke,</hi> and scourge, and then peradventure the Words of <hi>Adonibezeck</hi> may occur unto your Minds: <hi>Threescore and ten Kings, having their Thumbs, and great Toes cut off, gathered their Meat under my Table; as I have done, so God hath requited me.</hi> 'Tis no <hi>unusual</hi> thing to observe men <hi>paid</hi> in their own kind. The <hi>Providence</hi> of God, that superin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:41744:22"/> the <hi>affairs</hi> of the world, doth very frequently <hi>retaliate,</hi> and punish men by the <hi>same Rods,</hi> by which they have <hi>punished</hi> and <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted</hi> others; 'Tis observed that the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Guise,</hi> and the <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> were slain in the very same <hi>Room</hi> in which they had sat, and contrived the <hi>Bartholomew Massacre. Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France</hi> was murthered by <hi>Clement</hi> the Monk at St. <hi>Clou,</hi> in the same Chamber where he presided in a <hi>Consultation,</hi> to the same <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent</hi> and purpose: How <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth dyed, every one knows, that have read any thing in <hi>History;</hi> he expired <hi>wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in his own blood, and vomiting it out at all the Conduits of his Body, as a just Judgment on him, that had so barbarously shed it through all the Provinces of his Realm.</hi> They are the words of <hi>De Serves, vid. eum in vit.</hi> Caroli noni.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We make no doubt you would be willing to <hi>meet</hi> with Mercy from the <hi>Romanists,</hi> if God should at any time <hi>deliver</hi> you into their hands; you would be <hi>glad</hi> to find some <hi>favour in their Eyes,</hi> you would be loth to be ruined by <hi>Rogues,</hi> and brought to a <hi>Morsel of Bread</hi> by Informers, and <hi>Men</hi> of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and <hi>Rapine:</hi> We pray <hi>give</hi> to us what you would ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to <hi>receive</hi> from them; and if you desire to find <hi>Mercy,</hi> be careful to shew some bowels of <hi>Pity</hi> and <hi>Compassion.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>he that leadeth into Captivity, shall go into Captivity; he that killeth with the Sword, shall be killed by the Sword;</hi> If you will <hi>persecute,</hi> you shall be <hi>persecuted;</hi> if you will <hi>destroy,</hi> you shall be <hi>destroyed. Vediamo la crudelta tornore in capo ai Crudeli:</hi> The inhumane are oftentimes barbarously treated, and those that put off Man, are encountred with Beasts.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The World is a very <hi>uncertain</hi> State, all things in it shift and change their <hi>places:</hi> That part of the <hi>Wheel</hi> that is now on <hi>high,</hi> will instantly be on the <hi>ground;</hi> those that <hi>Lord</hi> it as they <hi>list,</hi> and prescribe to the <hi>Consciences</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of men, by an <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> utterly insupportable, may soon be imposed upon by Prescriptions <hi>equally burthensome,</hi> and a Pride as <hi>domineering</hi> and <hi>inexorable</hi> as their own.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The <hi>mutability</hi> of things in this <hi>uncertain</hi> World, was not unaptly <hi>signified</hi> by that <hi>humoursome</hi> fellow, that being asked by his <hi>Friend</hi> how he would be <hi>Buryed,</hi> answered, with his Face <hi>down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards;</hi> thereby <hi>intimating,</hi> that thô he were laid in the ground with a <hi>prostrate front,</hi> yet after some <hi>tract</hi> and period of <hi>time,</hi> he should revert and turn his <hi>aspect</hi> towards Heaven. We think it might be no unprofitable <hi>Meditation</hi> to those that <hi>tread us under foot as the mire in the Street,</hi> to consider that their <hi>day</hi>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:41744:22"/> may come, and that there are men in the <hi>World</hi> that are as <hi>Proud</hi> and <hi>Imperious,</hi> as <hi>Cruel</hi> and as <hi>Incompassionate</hi> as your selves, and that even we that lye now on our <hi>Faces,</hi> may stand <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right</hi> again; for God is able to raise and lift us up, and 'tis the frequent method of his <hi>Providence,</hi> to abase those <hi>that walk in Pride,</hi> and to <hi>give Grace</hi> and shew favour <hi>to the Humble.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VII.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We do most <hi>heartily desire</hi> you to consider, whether these <hi>Prose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions</hi> be ever like to obtain the <hi>end</hi> you intend and <hi>design</hi> by them: By them you intend either our <hi>Conversion</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or our utter Subversion and <hi>Destruction.</hi> We have said already, that Arguments taken from the <hi>sale of our Goods,</hi> the Imprisonment of our <hi>Persons,</hi> and Seizure of our <hi>Estates,</hi> have no force nor <hi>cogency</hi> upon our minds; they are no more <hi>affected</hi> with them, than our <hi>Eyes</hi> are with the sound of an <hi>Organ,</hi> or our <hi>Taste</hi> with the beams of <hi>Light,</hi> and lustre of the <hi>Sun. Without doubt</hi> (sayes a very grave Historian) <hi>we have learned by experience, that Religion is neither planted nor rooted out by violent means. Mens Consciences must be gently intreated, not violently forced.</hi> De Sorres.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But if you should design to <hi>destroy us,</hi> give us leave to ask you, whether you do <hi>imagine</hi> the present <hi>Prosecutions</hi> a probable or likely means of <hi>accomplishing it?</hi> have you never read the <hi>Histo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> of past Ages and <hi>Generations?</hi> do you know nothing of <hi>former times?</hi> have you never observed <hi>such means</hi> fail, and such <hi>attempts</hi> prove utterly unsuccessful? 'twere easie to produce <hi>Volumes</hi> of Proofs and Instances thereof without number. We shall mention the words of <hi>Du Plessis,</hi> in his <hi>Remonstrance</hi> to the <hi>Estates</hi> of <hi>Blois,</hi> where speaking concerning the <hi>Hugonots,</hi> in the person of a <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> he thus expresses himself: <hi>An Commencement nous les a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous brusles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>At first we burnt them alive, without any distinction of sex or quality; we were so far from destroying them thereby, that on the contrary, they extinguished our Fires by their Blood, and were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creased by our Flames: Afterwards we drowned them, and one would think that they multiplied like Fish in the waters. When their numbers were increased, we fought, and beat them in many Battels; but thô we defeated them, we could never overcome them. We made them drunk with Wine, or rather Blood, at a Royal Nuptial Festivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; we chopt off their Heads whilst they were sleeping, and within a
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:41744:23"/> few dayes we beheld them with our Eyes revive, and rise again as strong as before, and with Heads more hard and brazen than ever.</hi> Vid. Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moirs, Vol. 2. Pag. 23.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And what if your <hi>Persecutions</hi> should have the same <hi>effect?</hi> what if our numbers should be <hi>encreased</hi> thereby? and we dare <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> you, 'tis neither impossible nor <hi>improbable;</hi> for when we are prosecuted, and hunted like <hi>Beasts</hi> of Prey, the <hi>Common-people</hi> (that know no hurt by us, but only that we do not pray by your <hi>Liturgy,</hi> nor serve God according to your <hi>Laws,</hi> thô we do it accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>his,</hi> which a man would think should be as well) will pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and love us: They will think, that we are more <hi>likely</hi> to be <hi>the Servants of God,</hi> and of his <hi>Christ,</hi> than those that <hi>persecute</hi> and destroy us; They will think us more likely to be <hi>Doves,</hi> than the <hi>Kites</hi> and <hi>Hawks</hi> that rend us in pieces and <hi>devour</hi> us. They will espouse our <hi>Opinions,</hi> and come over to our <hi>Communion</hi> and Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yea, almost all those of your <hi>own Church,</hi> that have any sense or <hi>fear of God</hi> before their eyes, will be moved with <hi>Bowels</hi> of Compassion towards us: They will think us more worthy of the <hi>favour</hi> and protection of the Government and <hi>Laws,</hi> than those Sons of <hi>Cain,</hi> that seek our Calamity and Ruine. Some there are that have been <hi>sufficiently sharp</hi> against us, (and peradventure, much of the <hi>present Persecutions</hi> may be owing thereunto) who, we make no doubt, will be <hi>kinder</hi> to us within a little time, because we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they fear God. <hi>Relations</hi> frequently quarrel, and sometimes on pitiful <hi>occasions;</hi> but there is a radicated love in them towards <hi>each other,</hi> which prevails against all their Heats and <hi>Passions,</hi> and doth reconcile them again to a <hi>mutual tenderness</hi> and <hi>dearness.</hi> Good men may <hi>quarrel,</hi> and conceive little <hi>piques</hi> and <hi>animosities</hi> against each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, (so did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi>) but at the bottom there lies that <hi>fear of God,</hi> and love to each other, that will reconcile them again, especially, when <hi>one</hi> or <hi>both</hi> come to be afflicted and <hi>distressed. Hoop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> and <hi>Ridley</hi> were very good <hi>Friends</hi> when they were in <hi>Gaol,</hi> thô there were some little <hi>differences</hi> between them when they were at Liberty.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We find by <hi>observation,</hi> that among the Members of your <hi>Church,</hi> those that are most replenished with the <hi>Love of God and Man,</hi> and do partake most in the <hi>nature</hi> and Spirit of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> are the greatest <hi>Enemies</hi> to our Persecution; they do already <hi>pity us,</hi> and will do more as our Afflictions <hi>grow</hi> and press upon us: The learned Author of the <hi>Protestant Reconciler,</hi> the Author of the <hi>Conformists</hi> Pleas for the <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Bold,</hi> and the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:41744:23"/>
                  <hi>Countrey Conformist,</hi> all thorough <hi>Church-men,</hi> (but as we believe, of candid and Christian Tempers and Spirits) have sufficiently <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared</hi> that they are no promoters of <hi>Persecution,</hi> but have a very hearty <hi>aversation</hi> for it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And all men of the <hi>same Spirit</hi> will favour us, and oppose your <hi>Severe</hi> and <hi>Cruel</hi> manner of <hi>Proceedings:</hi> You will divide your <hi>own Church,</hi> and encrease our numbers by your <hi>Persecutions,</hi> and perhaps there may be <hi>no way</hi> of rooting out <hi>Dissenting Protestants in England,</hi> but by turning it into a <hi>Wilderness,</hi> which whosoever shall <hi>attempt,</hi> will in our Opinion <hi>attempt</hi> also his own ruine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <head>SECT. VIII.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We do beseech you not to be very <hi>forward</hi> in believing the Clamours and Outcries of your <hi>Clergy;</hi> when they Preach the <hi>Gospel</hi> of their great Lord and <hi>Master,</hi> we do heartily wish you would give a <hi>firm</hi> and unshaken Faith unto them, but when they give you <hi>Characters</hi> of the <hi>Dissenters,</hi> and make fierce <hi>Declamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> against the mischiefs of <hi>Separation,</hi> and variety of <hi>Religions</hi> (as they call it, in one and the same <hi>Kingdom,</hi> we do most humbly begg, that you would <hi>suspend</hi> your Faith, 'till you have consider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what are the <hi>mischiefs</hi> of a forced and <hi>constrained</hi> Union: we say with the <hi>Great</hi> Du Plessis; <hi>We do not doubt but that it were most to be wished, that in one Kingdom there were but one Religion, or rather one way of Worshipping the true God; such a Ʋnion cannot be too much desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and might we have our Option, one were more seemly than many; but since either the destiny of this Realm, or the disorder of our Church is such, that we have two, in troth 'tis better to permit them, than to ruine or weaken our selves, as hitherunto we have done, that we might have but one: In the Body of man, Maladies are sometimes continued for the sake of Health, and are as Remedies against those that are more fatal and dangerous: 'Tis a great trouble to have an Issue alwayes running in some part of the Body, and 'twere much better to have none at all, but 'tis bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to have it, and keep it open, than to close it up and dye:</hi> Thus that wise and good man, <hi>vid.</hi> pag. 41. <hi>ubi supra.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We do think it <hi>eligible,</hi> that all that profess the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus</hi> in this Nation, did worship him after the <hi>same manner,</hi> but we think it <hi>much</hi> better that they should <hi>Worship</hi> him after <hi>sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry manners,</hi> than that a <hi>great number</hi> of them should be <hi>destroyed</hi> and ruined; and we do wonder that <hi>all men</hi> that have <hi>Brains</hi> or <hi>Hearts</hi> do not think so too; for is it not <hi>better</hi> that <hi>twenty, forty,</hi> or a <hi>hundred thousand</hi> persons should worship God a little <hi>variously</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:41744:24"/> from our Constitution, than that they should be <hi>beggered, banished, imprisoned,</hi> or <hi>committed</hi> to the Hangman to conduct them to their <hi>Graves?</hi> Is it not <hi>better</hi> that they should pray <hi>without book,</hi> in their separate <hi>Meetings,</hi> than that they should pray without them at the <hi>Gallows?</hi> Is it not <hi>better</hi> that they should preach in <hi>Conventicles,</hi> than upon a <hi>Scaffold</hi> or place of Execution? In our Opinion it seems no great <hi>difficulty</hi> to determine these <hi>Enquiries,</hi> and we think that a little of the <hi>tenderness</hi> of the <hi>Christian nature,</hi> and some sense of humane <hi>frailty</hi> and imperfection, are qualifications enough for the resolution of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. There are many things <hi>desirable,</hi> that are not <hi>attainable</hi> in this World: 'Tis desirable that all the <hi>Churches</hi> upon earth, were of <hi>one mind</hi> and one judgment, but how to attain such a <hi>Ʋnion,</hi> who can tell? 'twere to be wished that <hi>all the members</hi> of the Church of <hi>England</hi> were good <hi>Christians,</hi> and did not only profess the <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of Christ <hi>Jesus,</hi> but live under the <hi>Power</hi> and Authority of his <hi>Laws:</hi> 'Twere to be desired that the persons that constitute our <hi>Parish Churches</hi> were of good <hi>Ʋnderstanding,</hi> sound <hi>Judgment,</hi> and exemplary <hi>Conversation;</hi> but <hi>how</hi> and by what <hi>means</hi> shall all these <hi>fine things</hi> be obtained? must men be <hi>Fined,</hi> Prosecuted and <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned</hi> for the <hi>want</hi> of them? or are those the <hi>proper means</hi> of obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them? Must we have no <hi>peace</hi> or <hi>quiet</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> 'till they be possessed and enjoyed? Then farewell <hi>Peace,</hi> as long as the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> endure, or 'till the coming of <hi>the new Heavens and the new Earth, in which Righteousness doth dwell:</hi> In short, we must take the <hi>World as we find</hi> it, and <hi>expect no more from it than is in it;</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Peace,</hi> Harmony and <hi>Agreement</hi> in Judgment, <hi>Affection</hi> and Practice is reserved for <hi>Heaven,</hi> 'tis very <hi>imperfectly</hi> obtained on Earth; those that cannot be <hi>satisfied</hi> with such an imperfect <hi>mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi> of it as this world is capable of, are the great <hi>Plagues</hi> and <hi>Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands</hi> of <hi>Christ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndome,</hi> and the Churches of God therein: Tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Faults,</hi> Differences and <hi>Imperfections</hi> must be <hi>connived</hi> at and endured, or else we must have either <hi>no Peace,</hi> or no <hi>seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Religion;</hi> intolerable ones must be <hi>restrained,</hi> and punished ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> it,</hi> and with such <hi>unwillingness, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay</hi> and <hi>tenderness</hi> as is agreeable to the <hi>Goodness</hi> and <hi>Kindness</hi> of Christianity. By these <hi>two Rules</hi> we do considently affirm, more <hi>Peace</hi> will be obtained, and with more <hi>advantage</hi> to true <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Godliness,</hi> than by any other <hi>means</hi> and <hi>endeavours</hi> whatever they be; what are tolerable, and what intolerable <hi>faults</hi> and <hi>errours</hi> of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <hi>Practice,</hi> we shall not discourse, others have done it, and there is no great <hi>difficulty</hi> therein.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:41744:24"/>4. 'Tis often said by <hi>Clergy</hi> men, and some others, (that should be better skilled in <hi>History,</hi> and the <hi>Misteries</hi> of Government, than to beleive it) that variety of <hi>Religion,</hi> or rather <hi>varieties</hi> in the same <hi>Religion,</hi> are prejudicial to the <hi>Civil Peace. This Maxim</hi> (saith a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great Man) <hi>hath much more</hi> devided <hi>us, than the diversity in Religion, that is among us, but either by the experience of what we see elsewhere, we must confess it to be false, or acknowledg our selves the most discordant, and unhappy people in the World. The</hi> Germans <hi>have two Religions in the same Cities, and sometimas in the same Houses, and yet live quietly, under the same Emperour, and Laws.</hi> We must there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore say, that they are not our <hi>Religions,</hi> but our <hi>Passions</hi> that trouble and desturb our <hi>Peace,</hi> and commonly they are the <hi>Pussions</hi> of such Men, as have no <hi>kindness</hi> for any <hi>Religion:</hi> The <hi>Switzers</hi> are partly <hi>Protestant,</hi> and partly <hi>Catholick,</hi> yet they live in a very great <hi>tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility,</hi> and free from all <hi>disorders.</hi> In <hi>Holland</hi> they permit almost all <hi>Religions,</hi> yet the Government is not rufled, or disordered by it. In the Cities of <hi>Mastricht,</hi> and <hi>Bois le Duc,</hi> the Inhabitants, are partly <hi>Protestants,</hi> and partly <hi>Papists,</hi> and live together in mutual <hi>Friendship,</hi> and <hi>Love.</hi> The <hi>Polonians</hi> have always had the <hi>Greek,</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Religion, they have had divers <hi>Bishops▪</hi> divers <hi>Synods,</hi> &amp; great <hi>difference</hi> in some important <hi>Articles</hi> of Religion, yet they never came from <hi>Words</hi> to <hi>Blows,</hi> but unanimously obey their <hi>Kings,</hi> and contribute equally to the Defence of their Country against their common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p n="5">5. These <hi>same persons</hi> are not wanting to give us evil <hi>Characters,</hi> and to lead us with <hi>infamous Titles,</hi> and appellations. We would most humbly beseech you to give no <hi>hasty credit</hi> to them, for whatever <hi>truth</hi> there may be in their other <hi>discourses,</hi> we do <hi>assure</hi> you, that what they say concerning us, is not <hi>Gospel. They report many things</hi> concerning us, which we believe <hi>they would not say,</hi> did they <hi>know</hi> us, or had they any <hi>conversation</hi> with us. They avoid us as <hi>Heathens,</hi> and <hi>Publicans,</hi> and then report all <hi>manner of evil</hi> of us ignorantly, and falsly. <hi>Justin Martyr</hi> complains of <hi>Crescens</hi> the Philosopher, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>That to ingratiate himself with the People, he publickly calumniated the Christians, as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theists, and Ungodly, when in the mean time, he was utterly Ignorant both of them and their Doctrine.</hi> Vid. Aus. in Apol Prima. pag 46. We have <hi>complained</hi> of it already, we now beg they may not be <hi>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lieved,</hi> till they prove what they <hi>affirme</hi> concerning us. <hi>Accusations</hi> were allowed by the ancient <hi>Romans,</hi> but <hi>Calumniations</hi> they abhorred, and we think twas <hi>just,</hi> and <hi>generous</hi> in them so to doe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:41744:25"/>
               <head>SECT. 9.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We would also humbly beg, a present <hi>suspension</hi> of the <hi>Laws,</hi> till His <hi>Majesty</hi> shall in his peculiar <hi>Wisdome</hi> think fit to call a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and ease us of the <hi>fear</hi> and <hi>burthen</hi> of them. We cannot but feel their <hi>weight,</hi> nor can we think it otherwise, than <hi>heavy,</hi> and <hi>oppressive.</hi> We are <hi>men</hi> as others are, and tho we may <hi>patiently</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the <hi>Penalties</hi> executed upon us, yet we cannot put off the <hi>sense</hi> of them, nor the <hi>desire</hi> of being <hi>freed</hi> from them. And to whom shall we <hi>Address</hi> our <hi>selves</hi> for <hi>deliverance,</hi> to whom shall we make our <hi>applications,</hi> for <hi>redemption</hi> from the curse of the <hi>Laws,</hi> and wrath of the <hi>enraged Statutes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We know not well what to doe. We are weary of the <hi>burdens</hi> that lye upon us, and would fain be <hi>eased</hi> of them, but how to get them taken from our <hi>Backs,</hi> we do not understand. We will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore the <hi>Intercession,</hi> of the more <hi>noble, generous,</hi> and <hi>Christian</hi> of our Adversaries. You have access to His <hi>Majesty</hi>'s presence, and liberty of <hi>approach</hi> before him, and would you but put on so much <hi>bowels</hi> of <hi>mercy</hi> and <hi>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpassion,</hi> as to become our <hi>Mediators,</hi> we are very confident you might <hi>prevail.</hi> You might set us at <hi>liberty</hi> from all our great <hi>Calamities,</hi> and our greater <hi>fears.</hi> You might restore <hi>smiles</hi> to our countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and <hi>joy</hi> to our Souls. We are <hi>now</hi> neither <hi>alive</hi> nor <hi>dead.</hi> We neither partake in the <hi>pleasures,</hi> and <hi>satisfactions</hi> of the <hi>living,</hi> nor in the <hi>rest,</hi> and <hi>repose</hi> of those that are <hi>departed hence.</hi> How easie a thing were it for you, to recover us from this <hi>dismal, dark,</hi> and <hi>uneasie State?</hi> With a few words of <hi>your Mouths,</hi> you might give life to <hi>many thousands</hi> of languishing Persons, and by your <hi>Mediation</hi> with our <hi>Great Prince,</hi> become their Temporal <hi>Saviours</hi> and <hi>Redeemers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. And what is there <hi>more worthy</hi> of your <hi>Greatness,</hi> and your <hi>Birth?</hi> What more worthy of <hi>Gentlemen, Englishmen,</hi> and <hi>Christians?</hi> What is the advantage of your <hi>Riches,</hi> your <hi>Power,</hi> and your <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> and why are they <hi>desirable?</hi> Is it not that you may do <hi>much good,</hi> and shew <hi>mercy</hi> to those that <hi>want,</hi> and stand in <hi>need</hi> of it? And have you not an excellent <hi>pattern,</hi> and a great <hi>example</hi> of it? Doth not God do good continually? <hi>Doth he not cause his Sun to Rise upon the just and unjust, and his Rain to descend upon the evil, and the good?</hi> And are you not bound to <hi>imitate</hi> him, and <hi>be perfect as your Heavenly Father is perfect?</hi> To doe <hi>good,</hi> is to doe like <hi>God,</hi> and 'tis onely the <hi>Great,</hi> that are capable of it, in any <hi>valuable</hi> degree or measure.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We are abundantly <hi>certaine,</hi> that you your selves <hi>are men,</hi> and liable to the <hi>same sins</hi> and <hi>imperfections</hi> with others of <hi>humane Race.</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:41744:25"/> Your Greatness doth not <hi>exempt</hi> you from the common <hi>corruption</hi> of Mankind, nor set you above the <hi>reach</hi> and <hi>influence</hi> of <hi>Temptations;</hi> You are Sinners, and will need the <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of God, as well as those of <hi>inferiour quality</hi> and condition. We are <hi>sure</hi> you will not dare to plead your <hi>innocency,</hi> before that God, who <hi>chargeth the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels with folly,</hi> and in whose sight the <hi>Heavens are not clean.</hi> We do not doubt, but that you will appeal from his <hi>Justice</hi> to his <hi>Mercy Seat,</hi> and Implore the Pardoning <hi>Mercy</hi> of God, and the Intercessions of our Saviour.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Will you need <hi>Mercy,</hi> and will you shew <hi>none?</hi> Will you have use of, and <hi>occasion</hi> for the connivence of <hi>God Almighty,</hi> and will you remit <hi>nothing</hi> to us, of the rigour of the <hi>Laws?</hi> Will you need the <hi>Intercessions</hi> of Christ <hi>Jesus</hi> with his Father, and will you refuse to <hi>intercede</hi> on our behalf with our Prince? Would you be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, that the <hi>Holy Jesus</hi> should present your <hi>Petitions,</hi> and <hi>Supplications</hi> to the great <hi>God,</hi> and will you refuse to present ours to the <hi>King?</hi> Would you be loath that the <hi>Son of God</hi> should refuse to doe the Office of a <hi>Mediatour</hi> on your behalf, and will you with an unyeilding obstinacy, and peremptoriness of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose and resolution, refuse to do that office on ours? Must we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no favour from you? Will you do nothing for us with our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign?</p>
               <p n="6">6. We are resolved to <hi>hope better</hi> things, and to be <hi>confident,</hi> that we shall not be <hi>deceived</hi> in our expectations. There is a <hi>Brave, Noble,</hi> and <hi>Christian</hi> Spirit, in some of those that are our <hi>Adversaries,</hi> and surely they will not see us <hi>perish,</hi> without opening their Mouths for our <hi>preservation.</hi> Tis to those that we make our <hi>Supplications.</hi> Tis those that we would make our <hi>Intercessors.</hi> Others we know, will beg <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> for us, unless it be <hi>an Ax,</hi> or <hi>a Gibbet,</hi> which are <hi>Favours,</hi> we doe not desire to receive, by their <hi>Mediation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 10.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We would <hi>humbly,</hi> and <hi>modestly</hi> desire, that whatsoever <hi>liberty,</hi> or <hi>favour</hi> is granted to us, may be without <hi>revocation,</hi> unless upon <hi>just</hi> and <hi>reasonable forfeiture.</hi> If it be granted us on this <hi>condition,</hi> we shall think our selves <hi>sure enough</hi> in the <hi>possession</hi> of it, for we never intend to doe <hi>any thing,</hi> that may occasion a <hi>seisure,</hi> or deprivation thereof.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But since 'tis <hi>hard</hi> to engage, for every <hi>individual</hi> in a Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, we would further intreat, that the whole Body of <hi>Dissenters</hi> might not forfeit the <hi>liberty,</hi> that may be <hi>granted them,</hi> by the faults and <hi>follies</hi> of some <hi>single persons.</hi> Let not the <hi>Innocent</hi> be punished
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:41744:26"/> for the sake of the <hi>guilty,</hi> nor those that <hi>peaceably</hi> use their <hi>Prince</hi>'s Favour, for the fake of those, that may <hi>turbulently</hi> abuse it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Though we shall be <hi>thankful,</hi> if his <hi>Majesty</hi> should only <hi>connive</hi> at our Liberty, and permit us the <hi>Worship of God</hi> after our own <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> and <hi>way,</hi> without any <hi>Security</hi> against the recalling of it: yet we must say, that to live in <hi>perpetual danger</hi> is a very uneasie State. Men take no pleasure to sit under <hi>drawn Swords,</hi> suspended by single <hi>hairs</hi> or <hi>threads,</hi> though it be at the <hi>richest,</hi> and most delicious <hi>Festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals.</hi> Few take any <hi>delight</hi> to stand upon <hi>Rocks</hi> and <hi>Precipices,</hi> espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if it be lawful for him that <hi>sits▪</hi> to throw them thence. We do not <hi>desire</hi> to live in the neighbourhood of a <hi>burning fiery Furnace,</hi> when every <hi>Rogue</hi> that hath abandoned <hi>God,</hi> and all good <hi>Conscience,</hi> may with impunity cast us <hi>alive</hi> into it. We would be glad to possess and enjoy our <hi>Liberty,</hi> with the <hi>Licence</hi> of his <hi>Majesty,</hi> and the <hi>Laws.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Were this granted us, our <hi>minds</hi> would be very much at rest, we should be free from those <hi>anxious cares,</hi> and <hi>fears,</hi> that do almost <hi>continually</hi> oppose us; we should with great <hi>alacrity</hi> mind the Business of our <hi>Callings,</hi> and with better Ability and <hi>Chearfulness,</hi> support the Government and Honour of our <hi>King;</hi> fear <hi>cramps</hi> and <hi>fetters</hi> the Active Powers of <hi>Mankind,</hi> it Freezes the <hi>Blood</hi> and <hi>Spirits,</hi> and makes them almost as <hi>useless</hi> as the Dead. <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Security</hi> infuses a <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Vig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur</hi> into the <hi>Souls</hi> of Men, and puts them upon <hi>Action</hi> and <hi>Employment advantagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> to their Persons, <hi>Families,</hi> and other <hi>Societies</hi> of Men.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Had we the Security of the <hi>Laws</hi> for our Liberties, we should sit under our <hi>Vines,</hi> and <hi>Fig-Trees,</hi> without any <hi>Fears</hi> or <hi>Consternations.</hi> We should all <hi>unanimously</hi> Love and <hi>Adore our King,</hi> as the Father of his <hi>Countrey,</hi> and the Common <hi>Protector</hi> of all his <hi>Subjects;</hi> we should be all <hi>ambitious</hi> of Serving and <hi>Contributing</hi> to his <hi>Grandeur,</hi> yea, we should be willing to adventure our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes</hi> for the making him one of the most <hi>glorious Monarchs</hi> upon Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 11.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We do with all <hi>humility</hi> beseech you to <hi>believe,</hi> that such hath been the <hi>Birth, Education,</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> of some of us, that <hi>nothing</hi> but <hi>conscience</hi> towards God, and fear of <hi>everlasting</hi> Condemnation, would have made us <hi>chuse</hi> the <hi>way</hi> that we have taken, and the <hi>party</hi> that we have <hi>espoused.</hi> We have not been without <hi>inclinations to Conformity,</hi> both <hi>formerly,</hi> and of <hi>late;</hi> since the <hi>Laws</hi> have raged so <hi>furiously</hi> against us; we having not been without <hi>temptations</hi> to have chosen the way, in which <hi>digneties, Riches</hi> and <hi>Honours</hi> are to be found, (nor do we think so meanly of our selves, but that we might have obtained
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:41744:26"/> our share in them) but <hi>Conscience</hi> hath laid those <hi>Blocks</hi> in our ways, that we have not been able to <hi>get over,</hi> nor we believe <hi>never</hi> shall. We have Transcribed some <hi>Paragraphs</hi> from <hi>Du Plessis,</hi> we will take the <hi>Liberty</hi> to take a few more <hi>Lines</hi> from him. Thus he expresses himself, speaking to the King. <hi>I shall without fiction tell y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur Majesty, that for these Twelve Years, and more, I have endeavoured by all means to become a Catholick, but hitherunto I have not been able to attain it; I have often considered, that after the fav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f God, there is nothing in the World so precious, as that of a mans Prince. I have Flesh enough to desire the Riches and Honour of this World, and not so little Spirit, but that I know, the Religion that I follow, is not the way in which they may be found: I set my self to read all the Books that I could find, I conferred with Learned Men wheresoever I met with them. My Flesh and Spirit always c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncurred to Fortifie their Arguments, and I desired nothing more then to be conquered by them.</hi> In fine Sir, <hi>I must tell y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur Majesty, my Conscience would, and did prevail against all their Discourses, alth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ugh it saw nothing but Disgraces, Losses, and Dangers, as the Reward of the Victory.</hi> Thus fare that good Man.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nothing <hi>almost</hi> could have better <hi>expressed</hi> the <hi>motions</hi> and <hi>pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions</hi> of our Souls, then the <hi>words</hi> of this excellent <hi>Person.</hi> We have not been without <hi>dispositions</hi> to have taken the way of <hi>serving</hi> God, that might have <hi>advanced</hi> us, or at least have supplied us with <hi>Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d,</hi> and <hi>Rayment,</hi> and necessary <hi>support</hi> for our Selves and <hi>Families.</hi> We have read, and <hi>considered,</hi> what hath been said to <hi>justifie</hi> and perswade <hi>conformity.</hi> Our own <hi>Flesh, Passions,</hi> and <hi>Affections,</hi> have Disputed <hi>earnestly,</hi> and <hi>subtilly</hi> in favour of it, but Conscience hath hitherunto prevailed. <hi>We are afraid of the Worm that never dyes,</hi> and <hi>the Fire that never does</hi> go out. We chuse rather to serve <hi>God</hi> in a poor and mean condition, with the approbation of our <hi>Consciences,</hi> then in, and with a more <hi>splended,</hi> and <hi>large</hi> Estate, to the regret, and <hi>offence</hi> of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We are not in love with <hi>Poverty</hi> and <hi>Rags,</hi> no more then we are with <hi>Sicknesses</hi> and <hi>Diseases.</hi> 'Tis no pleasure to us, to be <hi>distressed,</hi> for the maintenance of our <hi>selves,</hi> and those that are <hi>near,</hi> and <hi>dear</hi> to us. Some of us have <hi>Children,</hi> that would be glad of other <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yments,</hi> then a <hi>Wheel,</hi> or a <hi>Cart;</hi> and we have the <hi>tenderness,</hi> and bowels of <hi>Parents</hi> towards them, and though we do not desire <hi>great things</hi> for them; yet we cannot but wish them a little advanced above the common <hi>drudgeries,</hi> and <hi>servilities</hi> of life. But all this, and a great deal <hi>more</hi> we can endure, when we remember that our <hi>Lord Jesus,</hi> who was in <hi>the form of God, and thought it no robbery to be equal
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:41744:27"/> with God; yet took upon him the form of a Servant, and made himself of no Reputation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. We would be glad to have the <hi>favour</hi> of our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> and of his Inferiour <hi>Magistrates,</hi> and <hi>Officers. The wrath of a King is as the roaring of a Lyon,</hi> and the displeasure of his <hi>Ministers,</hi> and <hi>Servants,</hi> is uneasie enough, as we find by <hi>wooful</hi> experience. We take no pleasure in the <hi>frowns</hi> of a Mighty <hi>Monarch,</hi> nor do we chuse to be liable to <hi>thunder.</hi> We are not fond of the <hi>indignation</hi> of his <hi>Officers,</hi> nor is there any <hi>reason</hi> for it, that we can find. We should rejoyce in the <hi>favour</hi> of <hi>him,</hi> and <hi>them.</hi> But there is a King Superiour to him, and his <hi>Officers</hi> are much more terrible, and <hi>dreadful.</hi> If we cannot have the <hi>favour</hi> of them <hi>all,</hi> we will make that which we think the <hi>wisest,</hi> and the safest <hi>choice.</hi> We will chuse the <hi>favour of God</hi> (the great <hi>Soveraign</hi> of the World) and of his <hi>Angels, the Ministers</hi> of his Empire, before that of any <hi>Prince</hi> or Subordinate <hi>Officers</hi> upon Earth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 12.</head>
               <p n="1">1. The last request that we shall <hi>presume</hi> to make, is that you will please to <hi>believe,</hi> what we have <hi>said,</hi> in our own <hi>behalf,</hi> and <hi>vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> We do not know, that we have <hi>forfeited</hi> the reputation of our <hi>truth,</hi> or made our selves incredible by <hi>falsifications,</hi> and <hi>impostures.</hi> What others may have <hi>done,</hi> is nothing to us, we only affirm our <hi>own truth, uprightness,</hi> and <hi>Integrity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. What <hi>promises</hi> we have <hi>made,</hi> or may further <hi>make,</hi> in the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing part of this <hi>Discourse,</hi> we intend (by the Grace of God) to keep by an <hi>inviolable</hi> observation. We think we have promised no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but what is <hi>agreable</hi> to the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Gospel, and what is so we are bound to <hi>observe,</hi> and we will do it, whatever may be the <hi>effects,</hi> and consequences <hi>thereof;</hi> we hope we shall suffer no <hi>prejudice</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in <hi>time,</hi> but if we do, we will rejoyce in the <hi>prospect</hi> of the <hi>advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages,</hi> and compensations of <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. We do not doubt, but that there <hi>be those,</hi> that will endeavour to <hi>render</hi> all that we <hi>have said,</hi> or can say, <hi>suspicious</hi> and <hi>incredible.</hi> They are loath that we should have any <hi>favour</hi> permitted, or allowed us by our <hi>Prince;</hi> and to hinder it, will represent all that we say, as <hi>Faction, Romance,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrisie.</hi> They <hi>hate</hi> us with an <hi>implacable</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and would be <hi>very glad</hi> that all others might <hi>do so,</hi> and to that end, they expound all our <hi>Professions</hi> into dissimulation and <hi>falsehood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Whether you will believe us, (that surely are better acquainted with our <hi>own hearts,</hi> then those that revile and traduce us) or our <hi>niations;</hi> we cannot tell, but we <hi>promise</hi> our selves much from
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:41744:27"/> your <hi>Generosity, Justice,</hi> and <hi>Grandeur.</hi> We expect no great <hi>belief</hi> from the raging <hi>Furioso,</hi> and the railing <hi>Hectors.</hi> We have no <hi>hopes</hi> to be believed by the <hi>Foaming, Raving</hi> Persecutors. But we have some confidence, that those <hi>Sons of the Church,</hi> both among the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> that partake in the <hi>Christian Nature</hi> and <hi>Temper,</hi> will gain some <hi>Faith</hi> to our Professions and <hi>Affirmations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The Dissenters Resolutions.</head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 1.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WE will endeavour to walk in <hi>all good Conscience towards God,</hi> and towards Men. If we may not be <hi>permitted,</hi> to Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship God in our Publick <hi>assemblys,</hi> we will do it <hi>as we can,</hi> for we may not cease <hi>all Worship of</hi> the Deity, what ever it Costs us. When the <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rches of God</hi> were persecuted, in the <hi>Primitive,</hi> and more <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern</hi> Ages of the World, and could not have the <hi>Liberty</hi> of Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping their <hi>Maker, and Redeemer</hi> at Stated <hi>Times</hi> and Places, they Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped him as they could, in <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Groves,</hi> in <hi>Vaults</hi> and <hi>Grotes,</hi> in <hi>Charnel Houses,</hi> and <hi>Sepulchers</hi> of the Dead, and herein we shall follow their Example. If we may not <hi>serve God,</hi> and Build up one anothers <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Godliness,</hi> where, and when we <hi>would,</hi> we will do it, where and when we <hi>can.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. We will worship him in our <hi>Families</hi> by Reading, and Hearing <hi>his Word,</hi> by Sanctifying his <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> and calling upon his <hi>Name.</hi> We Read in the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Churches</hi> in private <hi>Houses,</hi> whether there were no other Persons, <hi>Members</hi> of those <hi>Churches,</hi> but the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of those <hi>Families</hi> we will not say (tho we judg the contrary most probable) but this we will <hi>Say</hi> and <hi>Do</hi> also, we will forme our <hi>Families</hi> as much after the likeness of <hi>Churches,</hi> as we are <hi>able,</hi> we will performe all those <hi>Acts of Worship</hi> in them, that <hi>Lawfully,</hi> and <hi>justifiably</hi> we may.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But especially, and <hi>peculiarly,</hi> we will <hi>Adore</hi> him in our Closets, <hi>Privasies,</hi> and Retirements. We will <hi>Prostrate</hi> our selves before his <hi>Foot-Stool,</hi> and power out our <hi>Souls</hi> unto him. We will review our <hi>lives,</hi> and enquire into the Errors, and <hi>disorders</hi> of them, we have reason to suspect that <hi>all is not well.</hi> God doth <hi>not afflict willingly, nor greive the Children of Men.</hi> We will search out <hi>those Sins,</hi> that have provoked the <hi>Devine Indignation</hi> against us, we will confess,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:41744:28"/>
                  <hi>Humble,</hi> and <hi>abase</hi> our selves before him, we will begg his Pardon, and hope he will not refuse us. We will get God of our side if we can. <hi>Quien a Dios tiene, todos las cosas tiene, y Quien a Dios no tiene, ninguna cosa tiene.</hi> He that hath God hath every thing, and he that hath not God hath nothing.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As we will <hi>take care</hi> of being <hi>Pious</hi> to God, so we will be <hi>careful</hi> to be <hi>just,</hi> and <hi>Righteous</hi> towards all Men. We will outrage no Mans <hi>Person,</hi> we inquire no Mans <hi>Estate, Reputation, Name,</hi> or <hi>Honour,</hi> but by the <hi>Grace of God,</hi> we will give to every one his Due. In breif we <hi>will Love our Neighbours, as our selves,</hi> and Love is the <hi>fulfilling of the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. In the conduct of our own <hi>Conversations,</hi> we shall observe the Laws of Prudence, <hi>Temperance,</hi> and Sobriety, we will have no <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> in the Licence, &amp; <hi>Luxury</hi> of the Age, God hath made us <hi>Men,</hi> and we will not Live as <hi>Beasts,</hi> he hath given us <hi>reasonable faculties,</hi> and we will not <hi>abandon</hi> our selves to the conduct of our <hi>senses.</hi> We have been <hi>Baptised</hi> into the Christian <hi>Covenant,</hi> and we will not Live like <hi>Heathens, Infidels,</hi> and such as are manifestly <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> and <hi>Apostates</hi> from it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>The Grace of</hi> God, that <hi>bringeth Salvation, hath appeard unto all Men, Teaching</hi> us, <hi>that denying all Ungodliness,</hi> and <hi>Worldly Lusts, we should Live Righteously, Soberly,</hi> and <hi>Godly, in this present World.</hi> This Doctrine we have been Taught and Learnt, and this we purpose, by Gods help, to Exemplifie in our Life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We will preserve <hi>true Faith,</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to our Prince. We will never depart from the <hi>Duty</hi> we owe him, what ever <hi>Provocations,</hi> injury, and <hi>wrongs</hi> we may receive from his <hi>Servants,</hi> and <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers.</hi> We have so great an Opinion of his <hi>Clemency</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> that we can never impute any of the <hi>Severities,</hi> that are exercised on us to his <hi>choice,</hi> or <hi>inclinations,</hi> if he <hi>knows any thing</hi> of them, or give any <hi>consent</hi> unto them, we must ascribe it to those <hi>Evil Characters,</hi> that are <hi>most impiously</hi> given of us, and that <hi>Force</hi> that is put upon his <hi>Royal Dispositions.</hi> For tis most certain, that the Subject, <hi>bien Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Sentoit du mal per lamain des Serviteurs, encore qu' il n'y eust que bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en au caeur du Maistre,</hi> doth oftentimes Suffer ill from the Hands of <hi>Servants,</hi> when the <hi>Master or Prince</hi> means them no Evil in the World.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If we Suffer, we will <hi>take care</hi> that we do not do it, as <hi>Evil Doers,</hi> and if we Suffer for <hi>well doing,</hi> we shall have the <hi>Apporbation</hi> of God, and our <hi>Consciences,</hi> and the support of an <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>upright</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:41744:28"/> mind, things in our opinion more <hi>valuable,</hi> than Crowns and Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. We may be prety well able to bear <hi>the rage</hi> and fury of <hi>Spite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and <hi>malignant</hi> Persecutors, whilst our <hi>Consciences</hi> acquit us, and we have the <hi>support</hi> of God; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> if <hi>Conscienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> charge us with <hi>guilt,</hi> and <hi>God depart</hi> away from us▪ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> must fall under their <hi>indignations,</hi> and utterly sink under the burden and weight of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. A Few wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nemies,</hi> are more eligible than those that are <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> and <hi>might<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hose that Persecute us, are a <hi>few poor impotent mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals;</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> must die and rot in the same <hi>common Earth</hi> with our selves; but God and <hi>Conscience</hi> are powerful and <hi>Immortal,</hi> and tho they be not <hi>numerically</hi> many, they are <hi>effectually</hi> more then all the World. Persecutors may <hi>destroy</hi> the Body, but God can <hi>destroy Body and Soul</hi> and <hi>cast both into Hell.</hi> Persecutors may afflict the <hi>outward Man,</hi> but <hi>Conscience,</hi> like a <hi>Vulter,</hi> preys upon the <hi>Soul,</hi> to its unspeakable <hi>anguish.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. If we may not have leave to <hi>serve God</hi> after our own way, with the <hi>approbation,</hi> or at least the <hi>Connivence</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> &amp; <hi>Laws,</hi> we shall not <hi>endeavour</hi> to prosecute it, by any <hi>unlawful Attempts</hi> or <hi>Methods.</hi> If we be Prosecuted for worshipping the <hi>Great God,</hi> and our Lord <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> in a manner a little <hi>different</hi> from the Consti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the <hi>Church,</hi> tho not from the <hi>appointments</hi> of <hi>Christ Jesus;</hi> we will bear it, and commit our <hi>selves to him that judgeth uprightly. Magni vias, &amp; potentes semel ulliscuntur propriis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iribus: probet &amp; innocente ipse Deus:</hi> The great and the mighty revenge themselves▪ but God avengeth the just and the innocent, saith <hi>Cardon,</hi> and to him we leave it. We will be no <hi>Rebels</hi> however we may be reported, or defamed. We will behave our selves, as it becometh the <hi>Religion</hi> of the holy <hi>Jesus,</hi> however we be treated by our <hi>Enemies.</hi> We will give <hi>demonstration</hi> (as we have done also already) that <hi>dissent</hi> in some things from the Establish'd <hi>methods</hi> of Divine Worship, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with unspotted Loyalty, <hi>&amp; que ce ne sont choses encomportibles d'estre bon Hugenot, &amp; bon subject tout ensemble,</hi> and that (to speak in our English Dialect) 'tis not impossible to be a good Subject and a Dissenter both together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 3.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We will <hi>patiently</hi> bear what is thought fit to be <hi>laid</hi> upon us; for tho we do not <hi>know</hi> that we have deserved those <hi>Severities</hi> from the hands of <hi>Men,</hi> that have been, and may further be <hi>inflicted</hi> upon us; yet we are sure we have deserved <hi>them all,</hi> and much more from the Hands of <hi>God.</hi> You are but the <hi>Rod in the Hand of God,</hi> and tho you may be unjust in <hi>persecuting</hi> and <hi>afflicting</hi> us, yet he is just in <hi>permitting</hi> you so to do. <hi>Absalom</hi> was a Rebel in taking Arms against his <hi>Father</hi> and his <hi>Prince,</hi> but God was very <hi>just</hi> in permitting it, as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:41744:29"/> Punishment for his <hi>Fathers Sins. Encore que Dieu n'ait point de part aux dess<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ins des mechans &amp; des meurtriers, il preside sur tous leurs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seils, &amp; sur tous leurs enterprises, &amp; il les dirige par son adorable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</hi> Although God have no hand in the designs of the mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous and murtherers, he presides over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll their Counsels and Enterprises, and Governs them by an adorable providence. (<hi>Dre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lincourt</hi> in his Charitable Visits, Part 3. p. 137.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The <hi>Physitian</hi> makes use of the <hi>gluttonous</hi> Appeti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of <hi>Leeches,</hi> and <hi>Magistrates</hi> make use of the <hi>barbarous</hi> and inhumane hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>r of Hangmen and <hi>Executioners,</hi> and God makes use of the <hi>serene</hi> rage and malice of <hi>Persecutors. Il s'en sert d'une facon admirable.</hi> He serves himself of them after an admirable manner; sometimes for the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stigation</hi> of his People, sometimes for their <hi>tryal,</hi> sometimes for their <hi>reformation,</hi> and sometimes that he may take them away from the <hi>evil</hi> to come. Besides, we are all mortal, <hi>&amp; il importe peu par quolle main nostre corps soit porté par terre, pourveu que nostre ame en sortant de ce co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, soit porté par les Anges au Paradis celeste,</hi> And it matters not much, by what hand our <hi>Bodies</hi> be sent to the <hi>Grave,</hi> provided that our <hi>Soul,</hi> when it goes thence, be conveyed by <hi>Angels</hi> into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Paradise.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. But this is no <hi>justification</hi> of those that Persecute us, or excuse of their Sin and Wickedness. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Pharisees,</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the <hi>Jews</hi> did nothing, but what was according to the <hi>Determinate Counsels</hi> and purposes of God, but they were <hi>barbarous</hi> murderers for all that, for they did not put him to <hi>death,</hi> to serve the purpose and <hi>decree</hi> of God, but to satisfie their own <hi>spite</hi> and <hi>revenge.</hi> And we are pretty <hi>confident,</hi> that those that <hi>afflict</hi> and <hi>prosecute</hi> us, will prove <hi>Persecutors</hi> at the last day, notwithstanding they do thereby nothing, but what accomplishes the <hi>Counsels of God.</hi> For we do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that their ends and Gods are not the same therein. God does it to <hi>humble</hi> and reform us, to wean us from the <hi>World,</hi> and to fix our hearts on <hi>Heaven.</hi> They do it to satisfie their <hi>avarice,</hi> their <hi>revenge</hi> and <hi>Serpentine</hi> hatred of all <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Godliness.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. We hope this <hi>free</hi> and open declaring of our <hi>judgment</hi> and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutions, shall not be improved to our <hi>disadvantage,</hi> and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we avow a purpose of <hi>patient</hi> Submission, that therefore our <hi>burthens</hi> shall be encreased. We hope it shall never be said, that since they make <hi>such professions</hi> of their <hi>determinations,</hi> to suffer what is imposed upon them, we will try them <hi>effectually.</hi> They shall have burthen enough. We have read of <hi>Julian,</hi> that when the <hi>Christians</hi> complained of the injuries, and oppressions they suffered from his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:41744:29"/>
                  <hi>Officers,</hi> he told them they were <hi>obliged</hi> to bear them, for such was the <hi>Commandment</hi> of their <hi>God.</hi> He excused the <hi>outrages</hi> that were offered to them, by telling them the <hi>Laws</hi> of their Religion, made it their <hi>duty</hi> to endure them. But we hope his <hi>actions</hi> shall never be drawn into <hi>example.</hi> We trust we shall never be <hi>oppressed,</hi> and our complaints answered by saying, You have promised <hi>patiently</hi> to bear what may be imposed upon you.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We will rather belive that our <hi>Resolutions</hi> of Patience and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission,</hi> shall be our Protection against all <hi>Injuries, Violence,</hi> and <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression.</hi> The Humble, the modest, and the Peaceable, should (we think) be treated with <hi>Kindness</hi> and Favour, when those only that are <hi>Stubborn</hi> and Rebellious, should be used with <hi>Rigour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But be the Issue and Event of these our <hi>Resolutions</hi> for Patience and <hi>Submission,</hi> what they will; the Practice of it is our <hi>Duty,</hi> and that we must take care of, while the Event and <hi>Effect</hi> thereof is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Providence</hi> and Disposal of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and appertains to <hi>God.</hi> We are obliged to obey the <hi>Divine Commandments;</hi> and to observe the <hi>Laws</hi> of Patience, Self-denial, <hi>mortification,</hi> Heavenly-minded<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, Contempt of the things that Perish, and others of the <hi>like nature;</hi> but whether the performance of them turn us to any <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage</hi> in this World, is a thing that we cannot <hi>know,</hi> nor must not <hi>determine,</hi> 'tis sufficient that they will be <hi>rewardable</hi> in that which is to <hi>come,</hi> and if we find it not <hi>here;</hi> (as we seldom do) we will hope for it <hi>hereafter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 4.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We will endeavor to make some <hi>advantage</hi> by our Afflictions and Calamities. <hi>Physitians</hi> make useful <hi>Medicines,</hi> and <hi>Extracts</hi> out of things of <hi>Venomous</hi> and <hi>Malignant</hi> Nature, &amp; there is almost nothing so <hi>Vile</hi> and <hi>Mischievous,</hi> which they do not turn to use, and Improve to the <hi>benefit</hi> of Man. The Flesh of <hi>Vipers</hi> is an ingredient in that excellent <hi>Treacle</hi> that expels <hi>Poyson;</hi> and is of use in inveterate <hi>Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> Pestilential, and <hi>many other</hi> Diseases. <hi>Quick-silver</hi> (a thing sufficiently noxious in its own Nature) after due <hi>preparation,</hi> becomes useful in many <hi>Distempers,</hi> and where <hi>other</hi> things have failed, <hi>that</hi> hath been successful.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Since our <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Estates</hi> are taken from us, and we are not permitted the <hi>Enjoyment</hi> and Possession of them; we will endeavour to lay up our <hi>Treasures</hi> in Heaven, where no <hi>Thieves</hi> or <hi>Robbers</hi> can <hi>Rifle, Plunder,</hi> or deprive us of them. We will do all the <hi>good</hi> that we can, whilst we are <hi>here</hi> below, and thereby <hi>lay in a good Foundation against the World to come,</hi> and what is laid up <hi>there</hi> we shall not <hi>doubt</hi>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:41744:30"/> to enjoy; for though we may be <hi>Outraged, Spoiled,</hi> and <hi>Pillaged,</hi> till we come to the <hi>very Gates</hi> of that <hi>happy</hi> State, we shall know <hi>no such things</hi> when once we are entred <hi>there.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. If we be laid in <hi>Goals,</hi> and denyed the Liberty of conversing with our <hi>Friends,</hi> we will fill up our leisure, and imploy our <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cancies</hi> in the Conversation of <hi>God;</hi> if we may not be permitted the <hi>Society</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> that are upon <hi>Earth,</hi> we will entertain our selves in the <hi>Communion</hi> of <hi>those</hi> that are in <hi>Heaven;</hi> though our <hi>Bodies</hi> be under restraint, our <hi>Minds</hi> will be at Liberty, and with them we will ascend on <hi>High,</hi> and make our approaches <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the City of the Living</hi> God, <hi>the Heavenly Jerusalem, and to the innumerable Company of Angels, to the general assembly, and Church of the first born,</hi> to <hi>God the Judg of</hi> all, <hi>and to the Spirits of just Men made perfect. Et si corpus includitur, et si caro detinetur, omnia Spiritui Patent.</hi> Though the Body be shut up, and the Flesh under Bonds, all things lye open to the view and Consideration of the Soul. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> in <hi>Lib. ad Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. When we are reviled, and defamed by the <hi>blackest</hi> and most <hi>infamous</hi> imputations, when we are compared with <hi>Highland,</hi> and <hi>border thence,</hi> when we are said to have made <hi>equal</hi> Defections from <hi>Primitive</hi> Christianity with the <hi>Papists,</hi> when we are reported to Prostitute <hi>dayly,</hi> the most Sacred <hi>Rites</hi> of Religion, to serve our <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cular</hi> interests, and are said to be a <hi>Scandal</hi> to the <hi>Christian</hi> Name, we will satisfie our selves in the Testimony of our <hi>Consciences,</hi> and the approbation of <hi>God:</hi> We know these things to be <hi>Gross,</hi> and <hi>Notorious</hi> false, and therefore, when they are reported of us, <hi>we rejoice, hoping that our reward will be great in Heaven.</hi> Illud maledi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum contemnendum est, quod beatitudinem creat, quod falso ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledicentis <hi>ore producitur. Jerome in loco.</hi> Our Lord Jesus was reputed a <hi>Wine bibber, a Friend of Publicans</hi> and <hi>Sinners,</hi> a <hi>Magician</hi> and an <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>Caesar;</hi> the Primitive <hi>Christians</hi> were reported to have worshipped the <hi>Head</hi> of an Ass, they were accused of <hi>Incest, Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, Eating</hi> the <hi>Flesh of Children,</hi> and other things of like Nature, as may be seen in <hi>Tertullian, Minutius, Faelix,</hi> and other of the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients;</hi> and if our <hi>Saviour</hi> and the most <hi>Eminent</hi> of his <hi>Servants</hi> were thus <hi>reproached,</hi> and belyed, we shall rejoyce in the <hi>Fellowship</hi> of their <hi>Sufferings</hi> and Reproaches, and in the hopes of <hi>Participaeion</hi> with them in their reward, and glory.</p>
               <p n="5">5. We are accounted and called the <hi>Pests</hi> of the Nation, we are thought unworthy to <hi>Live</hi> in the Land of our <hi>Nativity,</hi> we will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore endeavour to prepare our selves for <hi>Heaven,</hi> and do hope, that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:41744:30"/> if we be exiled from <hi>hence,</hi> we may be received and admitted <hi>there.</hi> Our case were very sad, if those that <hi>Persecute</hi> us were <hi>Lords</hi> of the <hi>other</hi> World; in the same <hi>manner, Degree,</hi> and <hi>Measure,</hi> that they are of <hi>this.</hi> We might then expect as little <hi>Favour</hi> there as here. But blessed be the God of <hi>Heaven,</hi> those that may banish us from our <hi>Houses, Lands,</hi> and <hi>Country,</hi> cannot keep us from the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> nor from an Inheritance in the <hi>Heavenly</hi> Canaan.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And seeing we can find no <hi>justice,</hi> at the <hi>Tribunals</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> we will appeal to that of <hi>God,</hi> who will judg <hi>the World in righteousness by the Man that he hath Ordained.</hi> And he is <hi>a Judg that accepteth not Persons, nor taketh rewards.</hi> And it will be time enough to be then declared <hi>Innocent,</hi> and have Sentence pass in our <hi>Favour,</hi> and we believe too timely and soon for our <hi>Enemies,</hi> and such as injure and oppress us. In the mean time, we will <hi>quietly,</hi> wait the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of that <hi>great Day,</hi> that will set all things at Rights, and <hi>give unto all Men as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ir works shall be,</hi> softly, and Calmely, saying, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ometimes am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dst our Afflictions, <hi>How long Lord, how long?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 5.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We will hope for <hi>deliverance</hi> out of our <hi>Afflictions</hi> in Gods <hi>due</hi> time. When God will deliver us, we do not prete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to know, nor is it our <hi>interest,</hi> or <hi>advantage</hi> to be acquainted therein, but thus much we think we may <hi>safe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> say, concerning it, when God shall have <hi>purged</hi> out <hi>our Dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ss</hi> and <hi>taken away our Tin,</hi> and when our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and <hi>Persecutors</hi> shall have filled up the <hi>Measure</hi> of their <hi>iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> God will <hi>come down and deliver us.</hi> And truly could we encrease in <hi>Holiness, Humility, Heavenly mimdedness, Mortification,</hi> contempt of the World, Love to God, and Man, and all other the Fruits of the Spirit, as fast as they do in <hi>Malice, Spight, Envy Rage, Oppression, Injustice, Hatred of</hi> God, and all <hi>good Men,</hi> with other the works of the Flesh, we might reasonably hope that the Evil Day would not be of any long Duration.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As we do not know <hi>when</hi> God will deliver us, neither do we know by <hi>what means</hi> or <hi>Instruments,</hi> he will accomplish it, nor have we any <hi>anxious thoughts</hi> about it, we know <hi>Gods Arm is not shortned that it cannot Save, nor his Ear heavy that it cannot Hear.</hi> God never wants <hi>Means</hi> to accomplish his <hi>own Counsels,</hi> when the <hi>fulness</hi> of time is come, he can make those that are our greatest <hi>Enemies,</hi> either with or besides their intentions, the <hi>Instruments</hi> of our Redemption and Deliverance. In the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, the <hi>German Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants</hi> were lamentably <hi>outraged</hi> &amp; oppressed; he employed all the Power of <hi>Spain, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> for their Ruin, he beat them
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:41744:31"/> in many <hi>Battels,</hi> took the <hi>Heads</hi> and <hi>Principal</hi> Persons of that <hi>Perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion</hi> Prisoners, and had Reduced them to that <hi>condition,</hi> that only the City of <hi>Magdeburgh</hi> stood out, and made opposition to his <hi>Arms.</hi> In conclusion, those that assisted to <hi>spoil</hi> and <hi>destroy</hi> them, formed a <hi>confederation</hi> against him, by means whereof some <hi>Liberty</hi> was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to them, for the Exercise of their <hi>Religion,</hi> and a Period put to their <hi>Miseries</hi> and <hi>Calamities;</hi> at least in good degree and measure. For this, those that please may consult <hi>Sleiden</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n his Comentaries.</p>
               <p n="3">3. 'Tis possible that those that now <hi>Persecute</hi> us, with so much <hi>rage</hi> and <hi>indignation,</hi> may calm and moderate their <hi>passions,</hi> and put on some <hi>bowels</hi> of compassion towards us. St. <hi>Paul</hi> was as serious a <hi>Zealot</hi> as most of them. <hi>He shut up many of the Saints in Prison, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing received Authority from the chief Priests; and when they were put to Death, he gave his voice against them. He punished them oft in every Synagogue, and compelled to Blaspheme, and being exceeding mad a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, he Persecuted them to strange Citie▪ Videte istu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> virum, una voce Domini ex Persecutore factum predicator<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m.</hi> Behold this Man, by one word of God, of a <hi>Persecutor,</hi> made a <hi>Preacher.</hi> August▪ <hi>in homilia sextâ.</hi> Tom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This is but one of those <hi>many ways,</hi> that lye open to the <hi>view</hi> of that God, whose <hi>understanding is infinite,</hi> by which we may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered. It becomes us not to <hi>prescribe</hi> to him, either the time or method, and means of our <hi>deliverance.</hi> Let him do it when, and <hi>how</hi> he pleases; we will hope for it, and with <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Resignation,</hi> expect it in <hi>his time,</hi> and whenever it comes, we will receive it <hi>thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully</hi> and give him all the <hi>praise</hi> of it. And if we should ever live to see that time, we will love God and Religion never the less, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring <hi>that the Captain of our Salvation was made perfect by sufferings, and that if any Man will live godly in Christ Jesus, he must suffer Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutions. Populus Diaboli persequitur populum Christi; dum adulteri per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequuntur Castos, infestantur sobrios ebriosi, homilibus insidiantur super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, benignos invidi, largos cupidi, &amp; eos qui mansuetudinem vel patientiā retinent, affligere non desinunt iracundi.</hi> August. Tom. 10. p. 777.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 6.</head>
               <p>Whilst our <hi>Afflictions</hi> continue, we will hope that our <hi>Supports</hi> and <hi>Consolations</hi> shall continue; and if the one <hi>abound,</hi> we will hope that the other shall <hi>abound</hi> also. Hitherunto God hath <hi>helped</hi> us; he hath been with us in <hi>Prisons,</hi> and in <hi>Dungeons</hi> we have had experience of the <hi>light</hi> of his Countenance. <hi>Plus in carcere Spiritus acquirit, quam amittit Caro.</hi> Our Bodily losses have been abundantly compen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed by the Spiritual advantages that we have found there. <hi>Dominus glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:41744:31"/> suam discipulis suis in solitudine demonstravit;</hi> Our Lord revealed his Glory to his Disciples in solidute, saith <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtullian,</hi> and to us hath he communicated of his Holy Spirit in Goals and Restraints. <hi>Hoc praestat carcer Christiano, quod eremus Prophetis;</hi> A Prison is of the same use to a Christian, that a Wilderness was to the Prophets. <hi>Auferamus carceris nomen, secussum vocemus.</hi> Let us not call it a Prison, but a place of Privacy and Recess, in which we are at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure to <hi>converse</hi> with God, and where we do <hi>never fail</hi> to find him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. We have suffered with Joy the <hi>spoiling of our Goods,</hi> we have seen our Houses <hi>rifled,</hi> and the Utensils and <hi>Furniture</hi> of them taken from us, by <hi>unmerciful</hi> and <hi>cruel</hi> Men; and all this with a <hi>calm</hi> and undisturbed Mind. We have, and do remember, that our Lord <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus</hi> had not where <hi>to lay his head;</hi> and we do not think it very likely, that our <hi>Persecutors</hi> will leave us <hi>meaner</hi> then the <hi>Son of God;</hi> who for our <hi>sakes became poor, that we through his poverty might be rich;</hi> and when we do co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll these things to mind, we do easily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the <hi>Spoilers</hi> to Plunder and Impov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>sh us, rejoycing in being made <hi>conformable</hi> to our Lord.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If God shall think fit to add to our <hi>Burthens,</hi> we shall hope that he will add to our <hi>Strength;</hi> and if our <hi>Calamities</hi> do encrease upon us, we shall <hi>verily believe</hi> that he will also <hi>add</hi> to the nature and quality of our <hi>Joys.</hi> If we <hi>must pass through the Rivers and Waters, we do not doubt, but that God will take care that they shall not ov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rflow us; If we must walk through the Fire, we will trust in God that we shall not be burnt, nor shall the Flame kindle upon us.</hi> If the <hi>Majesty</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will be with us, and <hi>Comfort</hi> and <hi>Support</hi> us in our <hi>Afflictions,</hi> (and we have no reason to distrust him) we shall have no cause to <hi>complain</hi> of the greatness or <hi>weight</hi> of them <hi>Mas quiero ser atomenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do en elprosundo del infierno, teniendo tu divina gracia, que gozar de tu gloria con tu offensa.</hi> I had rather be tormented in the lowest Hell with the Saviour, than enjoy all the Glory of Heaven with the offence and displeasure of God, says a devout <hi>Spaniard.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <head>SECT. 7.</head>
               <p n="1">1. We will <hi>Love</hi> and Pray for our <hi>Enemies,</hi> this was commanded and exemplified by our <hi>Saviour;</hi> He prayed for those that <hi>Murdered</hi> him, saying, <hi>Father forgive them, they know not what they do;</hi> we shall endeavour to <hi>imitate him</hi> therein▪ <hi>Amicos diligere omnium est, inimicos solorum Christianorum.</hi> All men love their Friends, but 'tis peculiar to Christians only to love their Enemies. <hi>Tertul. ad Scarulam. Delige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re inimicos tantum Christianorvm virtus. S.</hi> August. To love Enemies is a Vertue found only among Christians. And we are of opinion,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:41744:32"/> that 'tis <hi>impossible</hi> to be a Christian without it, and therefore 'tis very much our <hi>Interest</hi> as well as our <hi>Duty,</hi> to live in the Exercise and <hi>Practice</hi> of it, and by the <hi>Grace</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> we find no great <hi>difficulty</hi> therein. When we consider how many <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ndred Talents</hi> God hath forgiven us, we can easily remit <hi>a few</hi> to our angry <hi>Persecuting</hi> Brethren.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As we do <hi>forgive</hi> all the injustice, violence, cruelty and oppression, that they have <hi>exercised</hi> towards us, so we shall <hi>heartily</hi> beg of God to remit and forgive it, and all other Sins that they stand <hi>guilty</hi> of before him. It shall be our <hi>hearts desire and prayer,</hi> that none of their <hi>transgressions</hi> may rise up in judgment against them to their <hi>Condemnation,</hi> but that they may receive a <hi>full discharge,</hi> and absolution of all, and every one of them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. We will suppose, they will confess themselves guilty of <hi>sins</hi> against God, but whether they will <hi>acknowledg</hi> themselves faulty in any thing they have done a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us, we do not know. Our Saviour told his Disciples, that <hi>those that killed them should think that they did God good service,</hi> and 'tis not improbable, but that our <hi>enemies</hi> may be of the same opinion; but we have other apprehensions, and will be bold to say, that if those <hi>frontless lies</hi> that are reported of us, and those <hi>barbarous outrages</hi> that are committed against us, and that <hi>spite and malice</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they prosecute us, be <hi>service</hi> to God, we know not what it is to <hi>serve</hi> the Devil. Persecution is an invention of the D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d he is the great desirer and promoter of it. <hi>Athanasius</hi> in Apol. ad Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ium pag. 716.</p>
               <p n="4">4. We will make one <hi>Supplic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e on their behalf, and that shall be, That God will please to reform and amend their nature and their lives. This we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive will be a very useful and necessary request, seeing St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms that <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holiness no man can see God,</hi> and our Saviour Saith, <hi>that unless a man be born of God, he cannot enter into the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> We shall rejoyce in the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r Conversation and Reformation, and be very glad to meet them in the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of Heaven. We except not the very vilest and most mischievious of our Persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who find our selves under no temptation to wish them any evil, unless they think it an evil to be truly penitent, that they may be <hi>saved,</hi> which we do wish them with all our hearts, Heaven is sufficiently large to receive both them and us, that they and we both Repent, for their Advancement and advantage will be no prejudice or diminution to our Happiness and Glory.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 6. line 7. for <hi>savor</hi> read <hi>favor,</hi> and add <hi>such</hi> before <hi>sense,</hi> l. 8. for search, r. <hi>secure.</hi> p. 13. l. 3. for insolent, r. <hi>insolvent.</hi> p. 25. l. 2. for Transanctions r. <hi>Transgressions.</hi> lin. penult. for <hi>all<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> r. <hi>atone.</hi> Most of the other Errata's are only literal, which the Reader will easily discern.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:41744:32"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>